<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods rebuke in taking from vs that worthy and honourable gentleman Sir Edward Lewkenor Knight, the first day of May this present yeere 1618, he being at that time high Sheriffe of Suffolke whose Christian life and comfortable end are here faithfully recorded. Together with diuers profitable and necessarie instructions; deliuered first in a discourse at his funerall, and now inlarged, and published, for the benefit of others not then present. By T.O. aliàs P. minister of the word of God at Denham in Suffolke.</title>
            <author>Oldmayne, Timothy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113488</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848722</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848722</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13835</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13835)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1075:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods rebuke in taking from vs that worthy and honourable gentleman Sir Edward Lewkenor Knight, the first day of May this present yeere 1618, he being at that time high Sheriffe of Suffolke whose Christian life and comfortable end are here faithfully recorded. Together with diuers profitable and necessarie instructions; deliuered first in a discourse at his funerall, and now inlarged, and published, for the benefit of others not then present. By T.O. aliàs P. minister of the word of God at Denham in Suffolke.</title>
                  <author>Oldmayne, Timothy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 98, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Griffin for Iohn Parker at the signe of the Ball in Pauls-Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Timoth: Oldmayne, aliàs Pricke.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lewkenor, Edward, --  Sir, d. 1618.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13835:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13835:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Gods rebuke IN <hi>Taking from vs that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> and honourable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man SIR <hi>Edward Lewkenor Knight,</hi> the firſt day of <hi>May</hi> this preſent yeere 1618. he being at that time <hi>high Sheriffe of</hi> SVFFOLKE: Whoſe Chriſtian life and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>end are here faithfully recorded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with diuers <hi>profitable</hi> and <hi>neceſſarie inſtructions;</hi> Deliuered firſt in a Diſcourſe at his Funerall, and now inlarged, and publiſhed, for the benefit <hi>of others not then preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By T.O. <hi>alias</hi> P. Miniſter of the word of God at <hi>Denham</hi> in <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES. 12.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus man goeth to the houſe of his age; and the Mourners go about in the ſtreetes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edw. Griffin</hi> for <hi>Iohn Parker</hi> at the ſigne of the Ball in Pauls-Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13835:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13835:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>FLECTAR NON FRANGAR</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>ME list not ſcatch the hidden myſterie</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Garters</hi> Arte, or fetch thine antique ſtucke</l>
               <l>From Troian, Greeke, or Norman gentrie,</l>
               <l>Such pride I leaue to the vaine-glorious flocke,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13835:3"/>'Mongst whom vaine titles beare the greatest ſtroke;</l>
               <l>Yet ſome morality theſe ſeeme to yeeld</l>
               <l>Three Cheurones AZure, in an argent feild.</l>
               <l>Argent the badge of ſpotleſſe puritie,</l>
               <l>AZure heauens die: Cheurones a conſtant minde</l>
               <l>Three is the number of Diuinitie.</l>
               <l>Theſe in thine armes moſt ſweetly are combinde</l>
               <l>What good in heauen or earth we erſt can finde;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flectar non ſrangar,</hi> this his Motto ſpeakes,</l>
               <l>Although perchaunce he bends he neuer breakes:</l>
               <l>Not by the reckeleſſe ſtroke of diſmall Fate,</l>
               <l>Which hath but made this moralls veritie,</l>
               <l>Thy pureſt white hath got the pureſt ſtate,</l>
               <l>Thy conſtant minde the place of conſtancie.</l>
               <l>The ſwifteſt Creature will may be the creſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Grayhound.</note>To ſhew how ſoone thou gain'ſt this bleſſed reſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13835:3"/>
            <head>TO THE FAIRE, and hopefull Branch, of the <hi>renowmed</hi> FAMILY <hi>of the</hi> LEWKENORS in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> Edward Lewkenor <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been my continuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, euer ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence it was the Almighties pleaſure, to take from vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe, your worthy and
<pb facs="tcp:13835:4"/>
honourable Father, that ſome skilfull hand, would haue enterprized this worke, thus rudely by me both begunne and finiſhed. For the more beautifull the face is, the more exquiſite is the Limmer that it challengeth. (<hi>Let the Cobler meddle with his ſlipper, and let</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles <hi>only draw the picture of that great Alexander.</hi>) If ſuch a one would haue vndertaken it, how happie ſhould I haue thought my ſelfe if as his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, I might but haue ground his colours. But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none would; I as you ſee haue done it; Plainely I muſt needes confeſſe, howbeit as
<pb facs="tcp:13835:4"/>
neere the life as poſſibly I could. And to you, his only ſonne, doe I deuote this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, of ſo rare and onely a father. Your tender yeeres perhaps, will for a time dim your eye, that you ſhall not be able ſo clearely to diſcerne, that deale of worth that is here pourtraied, and ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out. But <hi>Pictures,</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beſt diſcerned ſome diſtance off; and therefore my comfort is, that although, not now, yet in time you wil: The which time being once come, let me deſire you, that whatſoeuer excellencie you finde here expreſſed, you
<pb facs="tcp:13835:5"/>
would be pleaſed, to imbrace, and follow; ſhaping your ſelfe and all your actions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſo noble, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Patterne. So, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer honours, your Father in his life poſſeſſed, you his ſonne after him ſhall be ſure to inherit, and the ſame bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings that attended him, ſhall queſtionleſſe, be doubled vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. The which I ſhall not whilſt I liue ceaſe beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging at the hands of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly FATHER. Alwaies reſting</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your poore friend, Timoth: Oldmayne,</hi> aliàs <hi>Pricke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13835:5"/>
            <head>CLARISSIMIS ILLIS viris, <hi>D. Laurentio Chaddertono S.</hi> Theol. Do<hi rend="sup">ri</hi>, &amp; M<hi rend="sup">ro</hi> Collegij Eman. Cantabr. <hi>D. Samueli Wardo,</hi> S. item Theol. Do<hi rend="sup">ri</hi>, &amp; Collegij Sidneij in eadem ACADEMIA Praefecto. <hi>NECNON Guilielmo Bedello,</hi> de Horninger, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanni Heyleio</hi> de Buria S<hi rend="sup">ti</hi> Edmundi, <hi>Thome Turners</hi> de Ouſden, <hi>Iohanni Plaifero</hi> de Debden, &amp; <hi>EZechich Edgaro</hi> de Halſtead: Paſtoribus vigilantiſſimis, Theologis digniſſimis, Amicis ſuis multis nominibꝰ colendiſſimis, TIMOTHEVS OLDMAINVS <hi>aliàs</hi> PRICKVS <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <p>MIrabimini ſat ſcio (viri dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſsimi, praeſtantiſsimi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologi) quae me noua ambitio
<pb facs="tcp:13835:6"/>
impulerit, vt quem hactenus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, illud <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, à publico omni hominum conſpectu ſecluſerit, nec paſſa eſt blandiens illa, &amp; ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca animi a forenſi ſtrepitu remoti quies (quam ab ineunte aetate ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diosè ſum ſectatus) for as prorepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, nunc derepente, neſcio quibus aeſtris agitatum videtis, in ambitioſo hoc, ſcripturientium theatro verſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, vbi cenſorum, cum ſpectatorum multitudine, contendere videatur. Nullum me (credite) anteactae huius ſolitudinis, coepit faſtidium, nulla conditionis nouae erexit affectatio, nullus gloriolae tumor inflauit, vt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter neotericos ſcriptores (in leui hoc praeſertim &amp; vmbratili ſcribendi ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere) nominis ſplendorem ambirem. Nuſquam mihi magis volupe erat, paterna ſpectare rura, &amp; proprij ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini fumum. Satis mihi eſt, abunde ſatis, minutuli huius, quod Dei Opt.
<pb facs="tcp:13835:6"/>
Max. munere conceſſum eſt, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbata poſſeſsio. Quaerant ſibi (ſi Dijs placet) naminis &amp; famae perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitatem, quorum animi ſuperbiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus gloriae ſtatibus intumuerunt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, &amp; furtiuis aliorum pennis, vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis loci volutent. Volutent (inquam) illi; ego ſatis mecum praeclare actum putauero, ſi poſsim humi repens, eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; obſeruare inſipientiam, &amp; irridere vanitatem. Nunc verò (vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri clariſsimi) eò loci res noſtrae poſitae ſunt, vt (vel vobis iudicibus) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queam me diutius continere; ex illo (quem dixi antea) quietis nido, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſus, cuiuſdam Theologi nimis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula diligentia. In illas etenim an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtias me adegit huiuſce hominis intemperies, vt vel ſcribendo leuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, vel ingratitudinis non ſcribendo, notam mihi inuri patiar. Nimirum illud eſt quod inquit Comicus, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum auribus teneo, cuius ſiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuero,
<pb facs="tcp:13835:7"/>
ſiue dimiſſero, morſum non ſum effugiturus.</hi> Haec dum mecum penitius, &amp; diuturna adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita deliberatione perpendo, quod po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui vnicum, elegi (è duobus malis iudicio meo minimum) acerrimam potius, cuiuſuis homuncionis cenſuram ſubire, quàm vel minutilam, erga digniſsimum hunc virum, liberaliſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Patronum, ingratitudinis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culam, feram mihi aſpergi. Deum interea teſtor, niſi crebris amicorum eruditiſsimorum, quorundam Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logorum efflagitationibus, propriaeque exiſtimationis (quam date veniam, ſi integram &amp; illibatam conſeruare cupiam) defenſione pertractus fuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem, nuſquam me, ne ſomniando qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem cogitaſſe, tractatulum hunc no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum (quem etiamdum typis indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſsimum iudico) typis euulgare. Ita mihi ſemper in delitijs fuit quod de Galba Tacitus, <hi>Famae nec incuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſus,
<pb facs="tcp:13835:7"/>
nec venditor.</hi> Eſto tamen, (quandoquidem non poſſunt mea vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta) neceſsitas obtineat &amp; vincat. Eſt ſiquidem vel in minutilis hiſce (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que enim ſine hoc cadit paſſerculus) ductus diuinae prouidentiae; quem ego libenter ſequor, ſi haec tantùm duo, quae ardentiſsimis votis efflagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, exorauero. Primò igitur a Deo Opt. Max. ſupplex peto, vt conati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus hiſce noſtris, vtut tenuiſsimis, fauſtè &amp; foeliciter aſpiret, vt cedant in nominis ſui gloriam, &amp; Eccleſiae vtilitatem. Nimirum vt digniſsimi huiuſce, generoſiſsimi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Equitis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam (rudiori fortaſſe Minerua elucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratam, &amp; feſtinante deſcriptam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamo) in exemplum ſibi proponant, cuiuſuis conditionis homines, Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, Pietatis, Religionis. Deinde au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, vt ſubitaneus huius ſtellae occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, languidam illam, &amp; torpentem, qua ſopiri quamplurimos videmus,
<pb facs="tcp:13835:8"/>
ſecuritatem diſcutiat. Exempla mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rientium (vti ferunt) ſunt docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta viuentium; Futurique mali praeſagium ſemper fuit, bonorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritus. Perſpicimus, etiamdum, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeri perſpicimus, ſeuientem vltricem Omnipotentis dextram. Vixdum illo defuncto,<note place="margin">Dom. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; Edn. undu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baconem de Shrub Armigetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> geminos inſuper, Reipub, fulera, Eccleſiae columnas, ſummae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritatis, &amp; religionis firmamenta, quantiuis pretij viros, efferri vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Enimuero, dum igneam illam nuperrimè impreſsionem obſeruaui, comantes ſpargentem iubas, &amp; coeli palatia occupantem; nulla mihi in mentem venerunt delirantium Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logorum placita; quin ſuſpicatus ſum (ſi liceat <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ex beatiſsimis hiſce Animabus, aliquam potius, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiſsimo flagrantem zelo, noſtrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſalutis deſiderio incenſam, poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiae praeconem, nonaeque vitae mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitorem de coele ſplendeſcere.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13835:8"/>Alterum eſt, quod à vobis effla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gito (viri praeſtantiſsimi) vt digne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini noſtrum hoc <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entelam veſtram placidè ſuſcipere. Qui eo tantum nomine, ſub auſpicijs veſtris prodire geſtit, quod ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferto illo beneuolorum, choro, nullos inuenerit noſter hic <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> famae ſuae ſtudioſiores: Nullum vos (expertus loquor) doctrinae veſtrae, &amp; pietatis amantiorem. Hac ego primum ſpe fretus, ſub amoris veſtri vmbraculo deliteſcere cupiebam. Nec poteram apud me cogitare, non futurum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis gratiſsimum, quod ad memoriae cius perpetuitatem conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruandam, vel tantillum faceret. Valete (viri gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſsimi) &amp; mendas omnes Typogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicas, calamo emendate; Authoris autem, ſub amoris tegumento vela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te; Clamidemque veſtram, quod olim Eliz aeo Eliae mihi circumijcite. Deus conatibus veſtris ſanctiſsimis
<pb facs="tcp:13835:9"/>
iuxta, &amp; pijſsimis foelicem ſucceſſum praebeat.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13835:9"/>
            <head>GODS Rebuke.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 39. verſ. 11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>When thou with rebuke doeſt chaſtice man for iniquity, thou as a moth makeſt his beauty to conſume: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euery man is vanitie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S oft as I haue conſidered with my ſelfe (ſince this heauie accident befell vs) of the worth and dignitie of him whoſe body we haue now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the earth; ſo oft hath the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration thereof made mee (though in vaine) deſire either a longer time, or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13835:10"/>
more daies for the better fitting of our ſelues for the ſolemnizing of thoſe his Funerals: or ſeeing that neceſſitie dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs within the compaſſe of one: that then we could with <hi>Ioſua</hi> lengthen this our day making of one, two; yea if it might be, of euery houre of the ſame, a day, that ſo nothing might haue beene wanting in the leaſt reſpect; for the further adorning and ſetting forth of theſe his Funerall ſolemnities. For ſhall we indeed ſuffer ſo faire a ſtar as this, thus fatally to paſſe away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more remembrance? But it is the hand of God that hath done it,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 39.9.</note> let vs be ſilent, it cannot be auoided, let it therefore with<note n="b" place="margin">Apo. 13.10. Heb. 10.13.</note> patience be indured. Neither doe we diſpaire at all of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable cenſure of wiſe and vertuous men, for our more then ordinarie haſt (as may be thought) in this his buriall. Eſpecially when as they ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it was the minde of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed in his lifetime, that things ſhould be thus ordered. Oft times in his health deſiring, of his deare Wife and now deſolate Lady: oft times of his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13835:10"/>
deareſt friends, that if God ſaw ſo good that hee ſhould end his daies before them, that they would be pleaſed as to ſee his body in a decent and comely manner committed to the earth; ſo in doing of the ſame that all needleſſe and ſuperfluous expences ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auoided: He deeming the money laid out vpon the ſame of all other worſt beſtowed, conſidering that vſually ſuch aſſemblies were rather meetings of not and exceſſe, then of any true humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Well then let others haue their pompous Obſequies, neither he nor we doe enuie them; And let them if they pleaſe hire Trumpets to ſound out and proclaime to the world thoſe their virtues, which till then the world neuer tooke notice of. Onely let the world but ſpeak what it knoweth here, and it ſhall be ſufficient for the honour of this worthy Gentleman, though none ſpeake for him, nor he now a word for himſelfe. Bury not therefore in obliuion, oh forgetfull and ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full world,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>His Piety and Deuotion to Godward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13835:11"/>2. <hi>His Integritie and vprightneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things indeed principally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing our conſideration here on earth, eſpecially ſtanding as they doe vpon record in heauen, being written (I make no queſtion) long ago in a booke of remembrance before the Lord: there they were recorded, and there they are now rewarded. And theſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are the two things that I purpoſe to inſiſt principally vpon in paſſing through the life of this worthy perſon: the which being done, and ſomething ſpoken likewiſe of his death: then will I by Gods fauourable aſſiſtance pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceed on to lay forth ſuch principall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, as that portion of Scripture, which according to the few houres al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted me, and I had leaſure to thinke of, will afford vnto vs.</p>
            <p>But before I come to any of theſe I muſt here craue pardon: Firſt if I ſhall more haſtily and with a drier foot paſſe through things, then is of the greateſt part of this Aſſembly either expected or deſired: ingenuouſly confeſſing that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13835:11"/>
at this time I am not at all mine owne, neither will Paſſion and Sorrow once free my heart, or ſuffer mee by any meanes poſſible to inlarge my ſelfe: my greateſt comfort being this, that the vertues of this ſo rare a Iewell are ſo well knowne, that the Iewell it ſelfe needeth nor greatly my commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: neither doth this <hi>Bleſſed wine deſire an Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>girland.</hi> Let mee hold my peace and the dead ſpeaketh ſufficiently, in the place of ſilence, he is not ſilent, he ceaſeth onely from his labours, and his workes they follow him.</p>
            <p>There is a ſecond thing likewiſe (which if it be a fault) then as for the former craue fauour, ſo for this onely a fauourable conſtruction: And that is for ſeeming as perhaps I ſhall this whole diſcourſe of mine thorough, with too dimme, and careleſſe an eie, to neglect and ouer-looke ſuch exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall things which notwithſtanding, in the veiw doubtleſſe of many here (ſure I am of the moſt part in the world) are held and reputed, of higheſt eſteem and reckoning. And theſe are <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13835:12"/>
of Familie: Generoſitie of bloud: Faire Lands: Large poſſeſſions:</hi> together with <hi>Natures richeſt beneuolence,</hi> thoſe <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuita dona</hi> (as the <hi>Scholemen</hi> tearme them) all which I confeſſe in no wiſe ought to be neglected, much leſſe contemned of any. For in doing of the one, man ſhall not diſcerne two things in God which are indeed moſt remarkable.</p>
            <p>Firſt his abſolute power in diſpoſing of theſe glittering things here in the world according to that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or good pleaſure of his. Secondly his infinite wiſedome in this his diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereby things thus forted ſerue moſt excellently not onely for order, but likewiſe for ornament.</p>
            <p>And then ſecondly, in doing of the other he ſhall not giue Honour her due according to that <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Cui hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, honorem,</hi> and honour to whom honour is due. Neither would I haue any ignorant (but where is hee that heard of this Worthies name that can be ignorant) how the worlds great Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactour was no Niggard at all in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13835:12"/>
euen of the faireſt of theſe his fauours vpon him.</p>
            <p>For firſt can that Familie, trow you, be of yeſterdaies beginning that hath brought forth ſo many? Or an ignoble ſtemme that yeeldeth eſpecially in this fading and decaying time of ours (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leed our winter) ſo honourable a braunch?<note place="margin">Deſcended of that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den termeth it, of the <hi>Lewke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi> His mother a Coheire of the <hi>Heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams;</hi> a branch of a noble Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in France vid. Mount his Eſaies. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, can it be an emptie or beggerly Fountaine which being ſeated vnder ſo rich and glorious an<note n="c" place="margin">The Church ſo compared, Iſa. <hi>4.</hi> and Pſal. <hi>68. Iudg. 8.2.</hi>
               </note> Hill was fedde continually with three ſuch pleaſant Rills, namely, <hi>Prudence, Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> and <hi>Temperance:</hi> whoſe waters neuer failed vntill at the laſt this cruell and vnmercifull Eaſt-winde dried vp, as you ſee, and quite cut of the pleaſant ſpring and ſourſe thereof. But in this ſo great variety let it be ſufficient for me to gleane (the gleaning of this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> being a great deale better I make no queſtion then the whole vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of many an <hi>Abieſer</hi>) though not euery thing that may happily make ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his greatneſſe or goodneſſe, yet at the leaſt ſome one or two, the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13835:13"/>
moſt principall which may ſerue a little to eleuate theſe drooping eies of ours, too much I feare mee fixed vpon his outward loſſe, to the due conſideration of his preſent gaine, and inſtant hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            <p>And theſe ſhall be no other but thoſe two things before mentioned, and whereof I deſired the world to take ſpeciall notice.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>His Piety to Godward.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>His Integritie toward man.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The which as they are in themſelues things moſt excellent, ſo doe they by reaſon of this their excellencie, more grace and beautifie him in whoſe breaſt they are then all the gifts either of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of fortune. For the beſt of thoſe doe but <hi>reddere virum:</hi> but the leaſt of theſe do <hi>reddere Diuum:</hi> By the others helpe a man may perchaunce go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond brute creatures, but by the help of theſe beyond<note n="d" place="margin">Being changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Chriſt <hi>2 Cor. 3.18.</hi>
               </note> himſelfe. But to ſpeake briefly of theſe things (as I may, not as I would) and the dignitie of the perſon deſerueth. Firſt for his <hi>Piety to Godward:</hi> who more pious and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13835:13"/>
then he? Witneſſe thoſe Sacrifices of his, the fruit (as may be iudged, if a man may iudge (as indeed he ought) the tree by the fruit) of a true and liuely faith.<note place="margin">Matt. 7 17. Luk. 6.44.</note> That wee may vnderſtand what thoſe Sacrifices were the better, wee muſt here conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Their Nature.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Their Number.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Their nature: they were Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, ſuch as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth in his firſt Epiſtle and ſecond chapter, verſe 5. terming them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſpirituall ſacrifices,</hi> in way of oppoſition to thoſe carnall and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall rites, aboliſhed and remoued altogether by the brightneſſe of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> comming.<note place="margin">Vſitatis est Paulo, quicquid eſt in fidelitus; &amp; à fidelibꝰ proficiſcitur, &amp; eorum fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſtatur Sacrificioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nomine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligere, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, for their number, they were theſe three principally.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Sacrifice of Praier, Praiſe and Thankeſgiuing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Sacrifice of reading priuately, and of hearing the word of God both read and preached publikely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Sacrifice of Almes and relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13835:14"/>For the doing of all which as he had his ſpecia I warrant, ſo in doing of the ſame none that I know more frequent.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the <hi>Sacrifice of Praier and Thankeſgiuing,</hi> hee had his ſeuerall Altars where he offered the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</p>
            <p>Firſt his priuate one where hee offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a ſpeciall ſacrifice twice at the leaſt, or thrice euery day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hee had his Altar more publike, where his morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning ſacrifice were conſtantly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <p>For well did hee conſider, that as praier is a ſacrifice to God, ſo is it a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour vnto man. It is that wherein God is much delighted, and Sathan moſt terrified, wherewith bleſſings are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, and plagues preuented. In pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie <hi>Iacobs Ladder</hi> whereby the ſoule of a Chriſtian hath a ſweet ſocietie with God: and in aduerſitie <hi>Noahs meſſenger,</hi> neuer ceaſing comming and going vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till at the laſt it returneth with an Oliue leaſe in the mouth, the ſigne of peace and reconciliation. This made this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13835:14"/>
Gentleman ſo carefull as hee was for the performing of this dutie, and that not only by himſelfe alone, but in company likewiſe with his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: no day euer paſſing him (to my knowledge) ſince he came to be a ſetled houſe-keeper, wherein his manner was not (whatſoeuer reſort was with him, or how great the buſineſſe was that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell him) to haue his familie gathered together, and there himſelfe (if no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter were preſent, after a chapter once read out of the old and new Teſtament, and a Pſalme ſung) vpon his knees not only to bleſſe that God that had giuen life and being both to him and his, but alſo humbly to craue of him whatſoeuer things he thought moſt neceſſary, in regard of ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>As for the ſecond,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
               </note> namely his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the word of God priuately, and hearing of the ſame both read, as alſo opened and expounded publikely, I ſhall not need to proue his more then ordinary diligence herein by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, where are ſo many eye-witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes preſent: and if they were not, yet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13835:15"/>
this our demonſtration were argument ſufficient; namely, the great meaſure of knowledge hee attained vnto in holy letters. Yea ſuch a piercing inſight into points of diuinitie the moſt abſtruſe and difficult, that as his iudgement of the greateſt Clerkes and moſt iudicious Diuines (both neere hand and further off) for the ſoundneſſe of the ſame was much approued; ſo was it for the more then ordinary ſtreine, and paſſing depth thereof, exceedingly admired.</p>
            <p>But here whileſt I am thus ſpeaking, I finde my thoughts at ſome variance and ſtrife within themſelues, whether I ſhould ſpeake rather of the matter of this ſacrifice, or of his manner of offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame. To end which ſtrife in a word, let the iſſue (if it pleaſe you) be this: That whereas there is no one thing the whole Scripture through more commended vnto vs either by varietie of arguments, or more noble conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence then the ſacrifice it ſelfe; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any thing in my conceit, whereof the moſt here (in this ſo iudicious and Chriſtian an aſſembly) haue a more
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13835:15"/>
honourable eſteeme then of it: for mee to enter any commendations of the ſame, were a meere lending of light to the Sunne, a labour altogether need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: and in the meane time a neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that light which this glorious Starre doth offer vnto vs, as a moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary direction for the performance of this ſo Chriſtian a dutie.</p>
            <p>Now that we may looke the better into the ſame, how he did it, we will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the Sacrifice into two parts, and will conſider of either of them briefly, and yet ſeuerally by it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And for the firſt of theſe, it is his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the word of God priuately and alone. A dutie indeed commendable in all, but admirable in him, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that it is not the faſhion for men now adayes, eſpecially of his place and greatneſſe, to take this courſe. And yet a laſſe amongſt many hundreds of his ranke and order (nay let mee offend none in giuing him his due) ſcarſe in an age is there not (eſpecially of his yeeres and time) ſuch another to be found; ſo generall a ſcholler, his vnderſtanding ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13835:16"/>
refined, his braine ſo pure, and in all kinde of learning ſo abſolute. All which hee promiſed from his cradle, in the graſſe ſhewing what the crop would be. And whereof (in my iudgement) that faire Mother the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> had a kinde of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <p>He was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen vpon a day of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie to make an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Colledge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue a yeers ſtanding; which hee did with great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe.</p>
                  <p>Midſommer Batcheler ſcarce three yeeres ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
                  <p>The death of his father and mother, dying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in little leſſe then twelue houres one of another.</p>
               </note> gueſſing happily by thoſe ſignes hee then gaue, whither his vertuous minde would at the length raiſe him: which made her ſo willingly to throw ſome of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours vpon him; and more ſhe would haue done, euen of her richeſt, had not a ſorrowfull accident ſo haſtily drawne him away from her kinde embracings.</p>
            <p>Now the Apoſtles rule is generally true, <hi>Scientiam inflare,</hi> that knowledge puffeth vp, and ſo in truth doth any other outward preferment whatſoeuer, either of nature or fortune, eſpecially thoſe in whoſe heart grace is not the principall ingredient: and becauſe there are ſo few in whom it is, therefore it is vſuall as I ſaid before, for the moſt in the world, if aduanced, though in a ſmall degree aboue others, as to haue an ouerweening of their owne worth,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13835:16"/>
ſo to haue a meane conceit of God, but eſpecially of his eternall word, either contemning it altogether as vnworthy of their hands, much leſſe their hearts, or vilifying the ſame in compariſon of other writings:<note place="margin">2. Kin. 5.12.</note> eſteeming with <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman, Abana</hi> and <hi>Pharphar</hi> (though Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of <hi>Damaſcus</hi>) more excellent then all the waters of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. But it was not ſo with him: for as hee honoured God from &amp; with his heart, ſo had he moſt honourably thought of his moſt bleſſed word. <hi>Alexander</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe neuer thought more highly of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> workes, then he did of this ſacred Booke. Neither would <hi>Cyprian</hi> bee more traded in the writings of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull. ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra in tanta admiratione habuit Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, vt nullum ſine eorum lecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one diem prateriret, &amp;c.</note> then hee was in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: hitherto referring all his former and latter readings, his knowledge in tongues and Arts; cauſing them all, not only as handmaids to grace and attend vpon this excellent Lady, but alſo as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary helpes to make her minde and counſell beſt knowne vnto himſelfe.</p>
            <p>As for the ſecond part of this ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of his, namely, <hi>His hearing the word
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13835:17"/>
of God read and expounded publikely:</hi> therein likewiſe we will obſerue briefly theſe three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>His Diligence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>His Reuerence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>His Remembrance.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt, namely, his <hi>Diligence</hi> therein, we are to know, that which few here can be poſſibly ignorant of, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his conſtant and continued courſe of hearing the word of God publikely taught, both vpon the Lords dayes, as alſo at all other times as occaſion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſelfe fit, both at home and abroad: and no maruell, for he was the ſeruant of Wiſdome, which made him with ſuch delight to wait at his Miſtreſſe gates, and to giue ſuch attendance at the poſts of her doores.<note place="margin">Prou. 18.</note> No weather euer ſo tedious, or buſineſſe trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, that could once ſtop or hinder him, but if ſhe called, he was ready at her ſeruice. I neuer in all my time can remember, if he were at home, that he miſſed vpon the Lords day comming to the Church both forenoone and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoone, but only the time of this his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13835:17"/>
ſickneſſe, then indeed he was two Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes away: it being as it ſeemeth now, the will of God, that neither then, nor neuer hereafter hee ſhould keepe any more Sabboths with vs here below on earth, and therefore hee haſtened him away to keepe with himſelfe, and the ſoules of the righteous, an eternall Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both in the new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that is aboue.</p>
            <p>As for the ſecond, <hi>His reuerend hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of the ſame: let that ſeat of his (no more his, but now the ſeat of ſorrow, couered to my thinking with a ſad and dolefull cloud) let it ſpeake I ſay whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer it ſhrouded, or were in the leaſt reſpect a Baud to any looſe or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerend behauiour of his: rather if it could ſpeake, it would tell a faire tale, though in ſorrowfull tearmes, of his Chriſtian behauiour, both in the time of diuine Seruice, wherein hee alwayes behaued himſelfe moſt deuoutly, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the Sermon time, whenſoeuer there was any (as ſeldome miſſed) moſt religiouſly either with his eare obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, or with his hand noting ſuch things, as he thought moſt neceſſary to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13835:18"/>
be remembred: The which behauiour of his made him to be both the more obſerued, as alſo honoured, euen in the hearts of them that otherwiſe knew him but only by name. I remember being vpon a time at <hi>Bury S. Edmond,</hi> and meeting with one by chance knowne to me, yet not knowing him: he deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of me, whether <hi>Sir Edward Lewke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> were that day at Church or no? I told him that he was: ſo I thought (quoth he) for in all my life I neuer ſaw a man of his yeeres and place, that gaue the like attention to the word that hee did.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third and laſt, is his <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of things heard: A dutie indeed neceſſarily depending vpon the other two, and making through the neglect of the ſame, the other altogether fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. For you muſt take the heart of man as it is not only <hi>plenum rimarum,</hi> full of chinkes and crannies, but withall you muſt conſider Sathan like a Vultur continually ſitting by, and with his noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome bill, to the vttermoſt of his power opening of thoſe paſſages, whereby it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13835:18"/>
oftentimes commeth to paſſe (the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger being not preuented) that thoſe things which are more ſubtill and pure, ſuch as is the word of God, together with the ſweet motions of the ſpirit, doe ſuddenly leake out and vaniſh away, leauing behinde them concupiſcence her ſelfe, together with diuers other carnall and noiſome luſts, like a thicke and helliſh aire to ſupplie their roome, and fill vp the <hi>vacuum.</hi> Now the onely thing to ſoader &amp; binde vp theſe crackes and flawes of the ſoule, is <hi>Meditation,</hi> and calling the word of God to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance when we are departed from it: Duties not only commanded vnto vs in the holy Scripture, but commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs by the examples of the moſt excellent that euer liued. And to take theſe two aſunder. Firſt meditation commanded <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18. <hi>Therefore ſhall you lay vp theſe words in your heart, and in your ſoule, and binde them as a ſigne vpon your hands, and frontlets betweene your eyes.</hi> And <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Let not this booke of the Law depart out of thy mouth, but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate therein day and night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13835:19"/>Secondly commended by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Dauid:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 119.40.</note> 
               <hi>Mine hands will I lift vp to thy Commandements which I haue loued, and will meditate in thy Statutes.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> commendeth that righteous man amongſt other rare qualities of his, that he is one that doth <hi>meditate in the Law of God night and day.</hi> So <hi>Iſaak Gen.</hi> 24. gaue himſelfe to meditation: <hi>Exijt in campum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Etſi quidam putant, actu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potius fuiſſe corporis quàm ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, ſeque exercuiffe currendo, ſaltando, vel domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ſuis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fabulando. <hi>Deut. 6.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe, vt aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienaret ſe à curis domeſticis:</hi> The more ſeriouſly to conſider not onely of the workes of God, but alſo of his gratious promiſes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, namely calling the word of God to remembrance, is a thing commanded <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. beginning at the firſt verſe, and ſo on almoſt the whole chapter through: where the ſpirit of God exhorteth to talke of the word of God in bed and at boord: <hi>hîc &amp; vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que,</hi> in all places and at all times: ſute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the counſell of the Apoſtle <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Let the word</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>dwell plentifully in you.</hi> Commended likewiſe firſt by the example of the Diſciples of our Sauiour Chriſt, whoſe manner was
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13835:19"/>
after the Sermons of their Maſter, to conferre of things heard, as it is plaine in the 13. of <hi>Matthew</hi> and elſewhere. Secondly by the practiſe of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelfe, ſo willingly aſſoyling his Diſciples doubts, and ſatisfying them in things that were beyond their reach And laſtly by the behauiour of them of <hi>Berrea,</hi> who frequenting the Sermons of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> (as it is plaine <hi>Act.</hi> 17.) did at their returne home, call ouer what they had heard, with all diligence ſearching their bookes, to ſee whether his preachings &amp; their Bibles did agree, eſpecially whether thoſe authorities that he alleadged out of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> touching (doubtleſſe) the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> were ſo or no. According to whoſe bleſſed example was this Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies practiſe, not only at other times, but eſpecially vpon the Lords day, wherein his manner was, beſides his priuate meditation and conference of the word of God with ſome ſpeciall friends of his, to haue his familie aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together immediately after dinner, and then after a ſhort praier by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13835:20"/>
him conceiued, to call ouer the princ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall points of the forenoone Sermon: as alſo before Supper to doe the like in egard of the Sermon in the afternoone: both which exerciſes right commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he was wont to conclude with prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er likewiſe, and ſinging of a Pſalme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus whilest others take their eaſe, others (as the faſhion of the times now is) deuote themſelues to vaine and idle recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and paſtimes, was this Noe (as you ſee) buſie at his worke in framing of an Arke, for the ſauing of himſelfe and his houſhold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither let me here forget one thing before I finiſh this Sacrifice, it came late to my knowledge, this morning, and therefore you ſhall haue it in the laſt place, (ſomething out of order you will ſay) but it is no matter, fall where it will, I owe it to the honour of this Gentleman. And it is, his extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary care that he had this laſt Eaſter, for the fitting and preparing of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and familie, for the right and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly receiuing of the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the body and bloud of our
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13835:20"/>
Sauiour Chriſt: all which hee did not only by praier, and reading of the word of God (his vſuall courſe at other ſuch times) but with the ſame he adioyned then a graue ſpeech, a zealous exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an houre long, wherein to the admiration of all that heard him, he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured as to informe their iudgements, of the nature and end of the Sacrament, ſo to quicken and ſtirre vp their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to come with a more hungrie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and appetite to theſe holy myſteries.</p>
            <p>The which ſpeech of his as it was <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra concio,</hi> ſo was it indeed <hi>Cygnea can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi> his ſweet and farewell Sermon, where whileſt he ſpake, his ſoule was (no queſtion) rauiſhed with that whereof he hath now the full fruition. That faire Riuer that he exhorted other to ſeeke for, he doth now ſit by, ſhading him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnder the tree of life, and ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe with the pleaſures of both.</p>
            <p>And this ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of the two firſt Sacrifices: now are wee come to the third and laſt Sacrifice of his, namely, his <hi>Almes and releeuing of the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13835:21"/>In treating whereof I purpoſe wholly to abridge my thoughts: and whereas much might be ſpoken, to ſpeake little, at the leaſtwiſe not ſo largely as I ſpake of the former; a word or two ſhall ſerue only as a taſte:<note place="margin">Arron by a cup of wine gaue the Gaules a taſte of all Italie. <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Camilli.</hi> And the xij. meſſengers that <hi>Ioſua</hi> ſent, by a bunch of grapes the fruitfulneſſe of the Land of Canaan.</note> for by a drop a man may eaſily gather the riches of the whole vintage. Diuers things I know are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at the hands of euery Chriſtian for the gracing of his ſacrifice, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it acceptable before God. But for breuities ſake we will conſider onely of theſe two.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That the Sacrifice be commanded.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That it be cheerefully performed.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is moſt neceſſary, that it be of Gods appointing, elſe it falleth within the compaſſe of that <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Quicquid ex fide non eſt, peccatum est: Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne:</hi> a meere <hi>Ethelothreſchie</hi> or humane inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a toy of a mans idle braine, and therefore by no meanes to be endured in the ſeruice of God. And as neceſſary likewiſe is the ſecond: the ſame Apoſtle ſhewing a like reaſon 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Nam hilarem datorem diligit Deus: For God
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13835:21"/>
loueth a cheerefull Giuer.</hi> Yea <hi>Curſed</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10.) <hi>is that man that doeth the worke of God negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently.</hi> Both which my deſire is may be well obſerued, ſeeing that by the one a man ſhall eaſily diſcerne, the worth of the ſacrifice, and by the other, his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe in offering the ſame.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the ſacrifice it ſelfe wee muſt take it, as it is indeed, a thing highly commended vnto vs in the holy Scripture both for the nature of the ſame as alſo for the great accompt, whereof it is with Almighty God. And therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> telleth the <hi>Philippians</hi> that it is <hi>a ſweete ſmell: A ſacrifice acceptable, and well pleaſing to the Lord.</hi> And the Authour to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> exhorteth the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.16 Deut. 15.11. Iſa 58.10. Rom. 12.13. Iam. 1.17.</note> and in their perſons all other Chriſtians, in no caſe to be negligent herein: aſſuring them that with the ſame and ſuch like ſacrifices <hi>God is well pleaſed.</hi> Neither is the Spirit of God more large in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending any one ſacrifice then hee is of this.</p>
            <p>And no maruell, for there is none
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13835:22"/>
beſides that I remember, whereby a man may either in the time of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, get vnto himſelfe a more aſſured teſtimonie, of the ſinceritie and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of his heart, or gaine a more ſacred anchor, which being faſtened vpon the promiſes of God in time of aduerſitie, he may, by meanes thereof certainely expect an iſſue both happy and comfortable.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of all which doubtleſſe, exceedingly incouraged and heartned on this honourable Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, as to doe the firſt the duty it ſelfe; ſo in no caſe to be negligent in the ſecond, but to doe it with all alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and cheerefulneſſe. Neither can the latter of theſe which is the onely beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the former, in my Iudgement better be diſcerned then by theſe two things eſpecially:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Frequencie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Conſtancie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For doubtleſſe the vncheerefull Giuer cannot hide himſelfe; but either he giueth <hi>nimis parce, aut non diù:</hi> Too ſparingly: or not long: his candle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13835:22"/>
ſodainely drowned in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Too ſparingly: firſt for matter, it is like <hi>Sauls</hi> offerings:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, the worſt.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.9.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, but ſpoiles.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly for manner it is <hi>Nabals</hi> feaſt now and then, once a yeare it may be, and it may be ſeldomer.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly not long,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the ſacrifice pleaſing them for a time,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.13.</note> but at length they ſnuffe at it, and it is a weariſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to them: It is like <hi>Sauls</hi> armour vpon the backe of <hi>Dauid</hi> which in the very proofe proues too heauie. But it was not ſo with him, his houſe being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ſeate of hoſpitalitie, and his gate the ſeate of mercie. A Stranger (if of any deſert in the world) was alwaies ſure here to finde louing enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement both of the Maſter himſelfe; as alſo of the whole Familie. <hi>Peter</hi> had a great deale worſe vſage, for comming onely to the high Prieſts fire, then a meaner perſon, yea perhaps one, that ſerued a great deale worſe Maſter, for comming to his Table. A ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, would in his houſe procure
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13835:23"/>
a kinde welcome, and ſeldome or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, did any depart from the ſame, without exceeding great content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Secondly as hoſpitality dwelt in his houſe; ſo did mercie at his gate, in a faire houſe built of purpoſe for her, whoſe doores like the temple of Peace, ſtood alwaies open,<note place="margin">Seldome vnder <hi>30.</hi> And ſome daies <hi>40.</hi> Their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion on the fleſh daies broath and beife, or mutton; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides bread and beare. And on the Fridaies Broath and Fiſh with bread and beare.</note> and great reſort there was of perſons daily haunting her courts: but eſpecially three daies in the weeke, when ſhe made more large prouiſion then ordinarie.</p>
            <p>Certainely a bleſſed ſight was it then (which no eye but one frozen in the place, could ſee, without bleſſing) to behold Chriſt thus feaſted in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and ſuch a number of diſtreſſed ſoules, aged perſons, and young chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the widow and the fatherleſſe, ſo plentifully prouided for. Neither did his noble and liberall hand hold it ſelfe ſatisfied onely with ſatisfying their hungrie ſtomaches except it did dilate it ſelfe likewiſe further, in prouiding couering for their nakedneſſe, and comfort againſt the iniury of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13835:23"/>
And therefore his manner was theſe diuers yeeres together, according to the time of his age, and yeeres of life, to diſtribute garments here and there to ſeuerall Townes, round about him (this yeere amongſt other giuing 32.) for the appairelling and clothing of ſo many poore and miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. I loue not to tell wonders, this is of truth, I lie not: Nay alas I ſpeake not halfe of that which my ſoule is pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to: of his Chriſtian behauiour in this kinde: For you heare me not ſpeak all this while (as I might) of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull minde to many other pious and religious vſes, maintenance of learning, releiuing of priſoners, to whom I haue knowne that hee hath ſent a braſe of angells at a time; Neither of his tender care that he had of his poore neighbors oppreſſed with ſickneſſe ſending them continually things neceſſarie for their comfort, and oft-times horſe and man for a Phiſician, to come to them to conſider of their eſtate, and to apply remedies accordingly for their recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie defraying all the charge of his owne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13835:24"/>
purſe. Theſe things I ſay with many other of like nature deſeruing indeede <hi>Caedar Tables,</hi> for breuities ſake I doe willingly omit, haſtily turning my ſelfe, to the conſideration of the reaſon and cauſe of all this, namely, what the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould be, that in theſe dead and lumpiſh times, wherein loue is waxen cold and liberality out of faſhion there ſhould notwithſtanding one be found, ſo liberall, ſo mercifull? now the reaſon I take to be partly, from nature, but principally from grace.</p>
            <p>Firſt for Nature, it were indeed a wonder that one hauing his breeding, deſcended of Parents, to their liues end, of ſuch renowne, and honour in the world, as for other their rare qualities, ſo for their bounteous and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall mindes; great hoſpitality, and tender affection to afflicted ſoules: for him I ſay thus bred to be baſe or miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, were not onely a wonder, but I ſay more, a thing altogether impoſſible; Eſpecially if wee ioyne with this, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, namely, Grace: (which if it were hereditary as the former oft-times is,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13835:24"/>
I might well ſay likewiſe, hee receiued from his worthy Parents) how euer not traduced, yet infuſed into that breſt of his, naturally inclined vnto liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, by meanes whereof his Faith did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuperabound to euery good worke. For how could it otherwiſe be,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.2.</note> ſo faire an <hi>Oliue,</hi> ſpringing from ſo rich and ſappie a roote, and ſeated in ſo luſty a ſoile, (fatted with the bloud of Chriſt, bedewed daily with the ſweete influences of his eternall loue, and the ſonne of righteouſneſſe, caſting ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall an aſpect vpon it) but it ſhould be alwaies flouriſhing exceeding frute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full?</p>
            <p>Neither muſt I here forget, in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how liberall this worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was to others: the exceeding libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality likewiſe and goodneſſe of the Lord toward himſelfe, dealing with him much what as he dealt with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> long agoe, in regard of that deare yet willing ſacrifice of his in deuoting to him his ſonne: Now ſee the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, hee tooke his ſacrifice wherewith he was highly pleaſed, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13835:25"/>
yet in the meane time <hi>Abraham</hi> had his ſonne: Iuſt ſo was his dealing with this worthy Gentleman: he receiued conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually this with other ſacrifices from him whereby he was much delighted, and yet for all this he had his ſonne, he inioying (my meaning is, in regard of theſe outward things) what poſſibly could be deſired. And certainely who is there eſpecially if acquainted with his eſtate, his commings in, &amp; goings out, but would haue concluded, that ſurely he muſt needes greatly hinder himſelfe by taking this courſe: and that either he muſt of neceſſitie abridge himſelfe of ſome of thoſe priuiledges belonging, eſpecially to men of his place and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; or elſe runne himſelfe into debt, or otherwiſe diminiſh his Patrimonie. But none of theſe I can aſſure you, and therefore a concluſion built vpon falſe principles. For firſt of all hee carried himſelf like a Gentleman in all reſpects whatſoeuer, whether you regard his apparell, his attendance, and laſtly his pleaſure, keeping as he beſt liked both Hawkes and Hounds as well he might,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13835:25"/>
not onely in regard of the abilitie of his eſtate, but ableneſſe of his minde; who knew right well to put a difference between the vſe and the abuſe, between a recreation now and then, and a daily and continuall practiſe, only vſing the ſame as phyſicke, to clenſe his thoughts and make him the more fit for the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of his calling.</p>
            <p>As for his owings I confeſſe he was in debt, the which for mine owne part,<note place="margin">His debts not aboue a thouſand pounds, of which the charges of the Shrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valtie came to fiue hundreth pounds of the mony.</note> I maruell was not double, conſidering that to my knowledge the yeere before he died, he disbourſed out of his purſe a thouſand pounds I ſpeak of the leaſt, more then ordinarie.</p>
            <p>But as for the latter, namely, making away or imbeaſeling, of any part of his Fathers inheritance, I may iuſtly ſpeak for him, as <hi>Nabaoth</hi> ſpeaketh for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>Abſit illi à Iehoua:</hi> Neither doe I remember that euer he ſould one acre, which if he did, then ſure I am, that for that one he bought two. No let this be the portion of him that forgetteth God.<note place="margin">Iob. 17.14.17.</note> 
               <hi>Let him, indeed be rooted out of his dwelling, and dwell in an houſe that is not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13835:26"/>
his; Let his remembrance periſh from the earth, and his name in the ſtreete.</hi> And let this Worthies portion be <hi>To ſcatter and yet more increaſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11.24 Eccl. 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let the bread that he throweth vpon the waters returne to him againe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.6.</note> Let him laſtly ſowe plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and reape plentifully, not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things alone, fading and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but ſuch things indeed, which are inualuable, peace of conſcience, a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dying name, together with that <hi>Euge ſerue bone &amp; fidelis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.21</note> in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
            <p>And ſo much likewiſe ſhall ſerue to haue ſpoken of his Piety.</p>
            <p>Now as briefly as you can deſire of the other, namely, his Integritie.</p>
            <p>Of which I ſpeake in the ſecond place, for that it is as I take it, a kinde of fruite, budding and bloſſoming out of the former; Neither muſt it be ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in any caſe, ſo farre as the word hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily will beare, I intending only there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Rectitude</hi> of his (as I may ſo tearme it) or that vprightneſſe of his conuerſation before men. A thing that <hi>Iob</hi> amongſt other excellent
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13835:26"/>
virtues is highly commended for,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>compl.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hee was</hi> (ſaith the Spirit of God) <hi>Rectus, a right downe man,</hi> as I may engliſh it, or as ſome will haue it <hi>Iuſtus erat</hi> a iuſt and true dealing man, much what like <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel, An Iſraelite in whom is no guile.</hi> Now that we may looke into the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of this Gentlemans conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation the better, wee muſt conſider him,
<list>
                  <item>1. As a priuate Chriſtian.</item>
                  <item>2. As a publike Perſon.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Neither ſhall he need at all to feare (his behauiour in both eſtates being ſo excellent) the verdict, of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, nor for his triall herein, refuſe at all, to put himſelfe vpon the ſame. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the world I confeſſe, be now growne old, and the elder in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, the more clowniſh and foule mouthed, ſeldome ſpeaking well of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ill of moſt, yea oft times they ſpeeding worſt that deſerue beſt at her hands: yet this quality ſhe hath, that when they are not, then to loue them, and when dead to commend them. Too Crocodile-like I muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13835:27"/>
neuer to reſpect a man vntill ſhee ſeeth his pale, and dying face. All his life time to ſtand, crying with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfull Buyer, naught, naught, and then onely when ſhe ſeeth him haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ſlimie vally, or that he hath already pitcht vp his Tabernacle there preſently to change her note with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Oh my Father, my Father,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the greatneſſe of her loſſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with her former ingratitude, well, this I perſwade my ſelfe will be her dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with this bleſſed Knight, whilſt he liued and ſhe inioyed, his comfortable preſence, then giuing him ſcarce a good word, or otherwiſe ſpeaking, very little of him that merited ſo much at her hands, writing continually in<note n="a" place="margin">The Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagorians wrot their anger and fallings out in water, &amp; whatſoeuer good deedes were done them in ſteele.</note> duſt or water that which deſerued ingrauing in ſteele or iron: yea oft-times for all his kindneſſe giuing him<note n="b" place="margin">Witneſſe the dealings of diuers of his Tenants with him at a generall Aſſiſes held at Bury S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Edmond, Ann. Dom. <hi>1614.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nabals</hi> thankes, yet now he is gone he ſhall be both iuſtified as alſo largely commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For inſtance let a bill be framed, and the worlds hand deſired.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt whether as a priuate Perſon, he were not a moſt ſtrict obſeruer of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13835:27"/>
his couenants? Moſt iuſt in all his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, his word, being not alwaies as good as a ſealed euidence?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly whether hee were not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> mercifull in letting of his Farmes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did gird of his Tenants with his Leaſes as the manner of Land-lords now adaies are (whereby things are as plentifull at their Farmes as it was at the rich Citizens in the 15. of <hi>Luke,</hi> where the poore Prodigall durſt not fill his belly for beguiling of the Hogges) and did not rather let them in ſuch a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable manner that his Tenants liuing vpon the ſame, were inabled, both to bring vp their children in good nurtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the feare of the Lord, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to doe good in thoſe places where they liued, as ſmaller wheeles mouing according to the motion of the greater?</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.9.</note> whether he were not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> louing to his ſeruants, and not ſterne and bitter vnto them?</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Deut. 24.14.</note> whether the hirelings-wages <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> were not duely paid him, to his full content?</p>
            <p>Againe, ſecondly whether as a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13835:28"/>
perſon a Magiſtrate his principall care were not to beate downe vice and to aduance vertue?</p>
            <p>Secondly, whether he did euer take a gift out of the boſome, to preuent iudgement, and did not continually, without any ſiniſter reſpect whatſoeuer ſet himſelfe, to ſupport the truth and ſuppreſſe falſhood?</p>
            <p>Whether, laſtly his whole endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour did not bend it ſelfe, as to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine good men and good cauſes, ſo to quell and daunt the prophaneſſe, and outragious diſorders of the times?</p>
            <p>Let I ſay ſuch a bill as this be now tendered vnto her and without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you ſhall haue her hand that it is <hi>Billa vera,</hi> a virdict true in all points: But ſuppoſe ſhe ſhould moſt ingrateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe, ſurely the matter is not great, ſeeing there are ſo many, and of no meane credit, whoſe ſorrowfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances are at this time in mine eie, who both knew the truth of this as alſo of the reſt that hath hetherto beene ſpoken concerning the bleſſed life of this worthy Perſon, and will be ready
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13835:28"/>
I doubt not vpon any neceſſary occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to auerre and iuſtifie the ſame.</p>
            <p>And thus haue I (I know not how) troden a bleſſed way, the way wherein this bleſſed man walked, and richly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned it was with many a delightfull flower. Thoſe that I haue offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, to my thinking were the faireſt. A clearer eye, perhaps (eſpecially in ſuch aboundance) would haue ſpied out many more, of like nature and of as excellent a gloſſe: but theſe though few, yet in my iudgement are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the diſcerning of thoſe two things, that in the entrance to ſpeake of his life, I propounded to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. His Piety.</item>
               <item>2. His Integrity.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And therefore contenting my ſelfe with the ſame I will leaue ſpeaking any further of his life, and come to his death, the occaſion indeed of a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Metamorphoſis here amongſt vs: <hi>Bethel,</hi> being as you ſee ſtrangely changed into <hi>Bochim,</hi> the habitation of delight into the houſe of mourners.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13835:29"/>Now for his death we are to know, it was much what ſuch a one as <hi>Caeſar</hi> deſired.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Short.</item>
               <item>2. Vnexpected.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Neither muſt I be miſtaken for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was vnexpected, as though this Chriſtian Gentleman, had either made a couenant with death and the graue, or put the euill day farre from him: doubtleſſe he that taketh but the leaſt ſuruey, of his vertuous life ſhall eaſily perceiue the contrarie; that hee rather (as appeared by his more, then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie imploying of his Talent) was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually expecting his Audit-day; when he muſt of neceſſity make vp his reckoning. And as for the tempeſt that is now falne, he did like a wiſe Pilot diſcrie it long agoe afarre off, and did not onely fit and prepare himſelfe for it, but did with many ſweete and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable words hearten on and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage his deareſt friends patiently to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, that which in his wiſedome hee ſaw, would not long be auoided: To vs onely it was both ſodaine, and in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13835:29"/>
very truth altogether vnlooked for: for who would haue dreamt of this ſome 12. or 13. dayes agoe? or what reaſon had we (who were in his company both eating and drinking, merry and cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſeeing him as like to liue as he was many a day before) to entertaine the leaſt melancholike thought of his Fata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie being ſo nigh? But let mee anſwer my ſelfe; reaſons there were many, but if none, yet his eminencie in grace had beene reaſon ſufficient: for the more the mountaine hath in height, the leſſe it hath in ſhadow, and the higher any perſon is in eſteeme with God, vſually that ſhadow of his (I meane his life) is wont to be the ſhorter. What remained after <hi>Heſter</hi> was fully purified, and euery way meet for the embracings of ſo mighty a Prince, but to be taken imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately into the Royall Palace? It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of <hi>Henoch</hi> that he walked with God: and preſently after the text ſaith, he was not found: and the reaſon is there likewiſe expreſſed, for God tooke him to himſelfe. Neither in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is it any way fitting, that ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorites
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13835:30"/>
as theſe ſhould be long abſent in this ſorrowfull vale, out of the preſence of that great Monarch of the whole world, who doth not onely loue them moſt intirely, but hath alſo ſo liberally prouided for them a ſatietie of pleaſure euery way ſo abſolute.</p>
            <p>And beſides, as we ſoothed vp our ſelues with vaine hopes in his health, ſo did we likewiſe the greateſt time of his ſickneſſe. Howbeit herein wee are not much to be blamed, wee being perſons beguiled altogether through the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full working of the maladie, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually hid it ſelfe in thoſe ſecret and vitall parts of his: neither did death euer vnmaske it ſelfe (but like a ſubti l Headſman went cloaked vp &amp; downe) vntill on the ſudden it gaue him his deadly blow. And ſurely the time was very ſhort, not many houres before his diſſolution, or euer wee had the leaſt ſuſpicion of the ſame. For is it not a ſtrange thing that the death of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſhould be a forerunner of his owne? The day before that his laſt, to our thinking and his owne feeling, his Feuer
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13835:30"/>
hauing quite left him. Nor did hee all his ſickneſſe through, ſhew himſelfe more cheerefull, nor yeeld vnto vs a more aſſured hope of his recouerie, then at that time. And therfore I would deſire all, eſpecially thoſe whom his death more nighly concerneth, to beare the ſame the more contentedly; ſeeing that now it is ſo eaſily diſcerned to be no other thing elſe but the meere pleaſure of God, thus haſtily (and in the flower of his age) to cut in ſunder the thred of his life. The blame I know right well will (eſpecially of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant multitude) be laid vpon that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man his Phyſitian, whom both for his great skill in that his ſcience, as alſo his extraordinary care ouer his ſo much reſpected a patient, I ſhall for mine owne part honour whilſt I breathe. But brethren let them and vs all know, that if God ſhooteth his arrow, it is not the ſhield of man or Angell that catching the ſame, can keepe it poſſibly from the ſides of him to whom it is intended. Neither is there any Balme ſo ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, that can heale the wound that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13835:31"/>
death maketh. Let him therefore haue his due, hee went as farre as Art could leade him: if it had pleaſed God to haue ſeconded his labours, wee ought (as I make no queſtion wee ſhould) to haue beene moſt thankfull; how euer, we muſt be content, knowing that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this be vnexpected of vs, yet of him long ſince determined, when theſe dayes of his were numbred that are now fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Againe ſecondly, that I may haſten to his laſt and dying breath, wee are to know, as his death was vnexpected of vs, ſo was it doubtleſſe for this Elects ſake exceedingly ſhortned: God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in anſwering him his continuall deſire, which was that in his laſt ſickneſſe his ſoule might part with as little ſenſe of the bodies miſerie as might be. For we are to know, that vntill the Thurſday at night before his death (hee dying the euening following) and only ſome two or three houres preceding his end, his paines were not great, but only ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>Symptomes</hi> as commonly attend vpon a <hi>Tertian Ague.</hi> Howbeit, vpon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13835:31"/>
the Thurſday at night about 9. or 10. of the clocke, hee grew (contrary to our expectation) much fainter, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his breath farre ſhorter then he had done all the time of his ſickneſſe before, yet wee ſtill held our former thoughts, hoping of his recouerie, vntill betweene 10. and 11. of the clocke at night, when death ſhewed her ſelfe plainly ſtriking him to the heart with a ſudden cold, and inſtantly benumming of one of his armes. I will not here ſpend time in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out what the reaſon ſhould be of this his ſo ſudden a change: whether he tooke cold lying too thinne clad in his bed all the day before, or whether ſome cold vapour piercing in at his window, he ſitting too nigh the ſame after he was vp, drew the malignant qualitie inward to his heart; or whether neither of theſe, but only the immediate hand of God, in haſtening of his end, indeed the moſt probable. <hi>In dubijs dubiè:</hi> Let it onely be ſufficient for vs to know, that within one quarter of an houres ſpace through the wiſdome and great skill of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian his arme and body were reſtored
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13835:32"/>
to their former temper, and himſelfe likewiſe after a while brought to take ſome tolerable reſt. Notwithſtanding in the morning there wee eaſily diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in him a great alteration, it being by this time written in his countenance whither he would. And yet at that very time, and ſo diuers houres after, he was of ſo ſtrong and able a body, that wee did not at all imagine that his departure had beene ſo nigh, but perſwaded our ſelues that he might liue at the leaſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the morrow after, which was the eleuenth, and his criticall day. But God (as the euent ſhewed) had otherwiſe determined, appointing that day to be his laſt, with the end whereof he ſhould end his life: vpon which day (it being as we know according to the time of the yeere <hi>May-day</hi>) his deſire was in the morning to be remoued into another chamber, intending only (as it ſhould ſeeme) there to reſt himſelfe for a time, before hee ſhould remoue into the chamber of ſo great a preſence. Well his minde is ſatisfied, and he accordingly brought thither.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13835:32"/>After which time there was no appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent change in his eſtate to be deſcried in him, from that it was in the morning, vntill 6. of the clocke at night, at which time both his ſpeech, and (to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe about him) his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding likewiſe were at once taken from him. The newes whereof being brought vnto me (for at that time I was not with him) did at the firſt hearing ſomewhat amaze me, yet haſtening in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his chamber, I found the report too true, for there he lay as a man in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, neither hearing nor regarding: only to my thinking inwardly wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with ſome ſtrong and violent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation. Whereupon pawſing a while, I asked him whether he knew me? his anſwer to my thinking was <hi>No.</hi> Well Sir (quoth I) if you know not mee, I pray Almightie God giue you the full knowledge of him, in whoſe knowledge alone there is life eternall. But Sir it is your minde (is it not?) that we ſhould pray with you: what anſwer hee made me I could not well diſcerne; but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the anſwer was, wee regarded a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13835:33"/>
great deale more the preſent neceſſitie then the voice. Whereupon we all that were preſent there fell downe vpon our knees before God, and with what ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe of ſoule we could, we humbly beſought his Maieſtie to take pittie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in this his agonie, to giue him the ſweet fruit of all his former labours, and comfort of all thoſe bleſſed and gratious promiſes that carefully he had laid vp againſt this time ſpecially: not to ſuffer him to be tempted aboue his ſtrength, but to affoord him an happie iſſue with the temptation. Laſtly, if in his infinite wiſdome hee ſaw ſo good, then to affoord him (if it were his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at that time to take him out of the world) at the leaſtwiſe ſo much libertie as to giue ſatisfaction to the world of that full aſſurance that he had of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life, and his liuely expectation of the crowne of immortalitie.</p>
            <p>The which praier of ours was no ſooner ended, but it was for the moſt part as gratiouſly anſwered: for imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after was both his vnderſtanding and ſpeech reſtored vnto him, and hee
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13835:33"/>
thereupon ſuddenly brake forth into theſe or the like ſpeeches: <hi>Lord God Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houa haue mercy vpon me. Holy, holy, holy, Lord God haue mercy vpon mee. Oh Ieſu Chriſt that ſitteſt at the right hand of the Father, take pittie on me and pleade my cauſe. Oh thou good Samaritan, now powre thy wine and oile into my diſtreſſed ſoule. Father if the greene tree be cut downe, ſhall the Sire be ſpared? If the righteous ſcarcely be ſaued, what ſhall become of mee poore ſinner?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus he went on, we ſtanding in the meane time with watrie eyes about his bed, whileſt hee pleaded in this ſort his cauſe with God. At the length I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan againe with him, asking him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he knew me? He told me yes, and called me by my name. Sir (ſaid I) I perceiue well there hath beene a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict betwixt you and ſome great and eager temptation; but whatſoeuer it were, my hope is, that by this time it is vanquiſhed. <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my ſinnes, they are thouſand thouſands, millions of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands.</hi> To whom I anſwered, that hee did well to lay them forth to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13835:34"/>
ſhewing plainly thereby that his minde was not to hide any, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe all, as one heartily ſorry for the committing the leaſt of them. But Sir (ſaid I) let the number of them I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you no whit aſtoniſh you, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the manner of our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent him of his ſins, to remoue his ſinnes (though neuer ſo many) farre out of his remembrance,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.21.22. Mica. 7.19.</note> yea to drowne and burie them in the bottome of the ſea. And let them be granted ſo many as you ſpeake of, yet their number is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, but the mercy of the Lord you know is infinite.</p>
            <p>True (ſaid he) <hi>But my ſinnes are ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let ſinnes.</hi> Sir (ſaid I) be it ſo: but what ſaith God <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. <hi>Come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let vs reaſon together: Though your ſinnes were as crimſon, they ſhall be made white as ſnow; though they were red like ſcarlet, they ſhall be as wooll.</hi> But Sir (replied I) for that long diſcourſe may I ſuppoſe be troubleſome to you, I would deſire you in a word or two to anſwer mee theſe two queſtions: Firſt of all, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13835:34"/>
you be not heartily ſorry for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding God your heauenly father as you haue done, and whether that be not the only weight that now oppreſſeth your ſoule? He told me Yes, deſiring Chriſt to eaſe him of it. Sir (ſaid I) doubt you not of it, he will doe it, you and ſuch as you are being (as you know as well as my ſelfe) the onely perſons that hee in the 11. of <hi>Matthew</hi> doth inuite and call vnto him, promiſing aſſuredly to eaſe them of their burthen.</p>
            <p>The ſecond queſtion Sir (quoth I) ſhall be only this, whether you doe not hunger and thirſt now for the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt, preferring it before all the glory and riches in the world whatſoeuer? Oh ſaith he, lifting vp his dying eyes to heauen, that I doe: Well Sir, quoth I, hold out in this holy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of yours, you ſhall (my life for yours) be fully ſatisfied. After which diſcourſe of ours once ended, it cannot be imagined how wonderfully his heart was cheared, the Sonne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hauing by this time brought ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnder his wings: the loue of God
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13835:35"/>
like the Sunne oft times breaking out of a blacke cloud ſhining comfortably vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſoule: which made him deſirous, as wee well perceiued by him, to haue ſpoken much more. And as glad ſhould we haue beene to haue heard him; but by this time his glaſſe was run, and thoſe two louing friends, his ſoule and body I meane, were ſhaking hands, and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one another for a time farewell. The which I perceiuing, asked him whether I ſhould pray with him againe or no? <hi>Yes</hi> (anſwered hee) <hi>with all my heart:</hi> which words of his he drew out with a fainting breath, exceeding long: In the middeſt of which praier of mine, he was heard of ſome in whoſe armes he died, to vtter theſe words, <hi>Lord Ieſus I come to thee,</hi> and ſo lying quietly for a time (not ſtirring ſcarcely hand or foot) which is a thing to be wondred at, hee dying in his full ſtrength; within a ſhort ſpace after he yeelded that bleſſed ſoule of his into the armes of his Sauiour, in whoſe loue he ſlept. <hi>Qualis vita, finis ita.</hi> The <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> as you ſee in all points ſuiting the <hi>Scene</hi> forepaſſed, hee liued
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13835:35"/>
vertuouſly and died bleſſedly. The vſe that we are to make principally of both theſe vnto our ſelues, is this, that wee now all of vs follow his holy and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian example: imitating herein the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Pilot, whoſe manner is, paſſing through a troubleſome Sea, wherein is both <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis, Rockes</hi> and <hi>Sands</hi> dangerous and deuouring; if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance hee ſpieth a ſhip gliding along before him, guided by ſome faire and kilfull hand, and now entred the wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hauen, to follow her courſe with as little aberration as poſſibly may be: So I beſeech you brethren let vs order and diſpoſe our ſelues, making his courſe our guide, and his life our example. Let vs as little ſwerue from him, as he ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from Chriſt: ſo ſhall we without queſtion meet at the length comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly together in that bleſſed Hauen where hee hath now caſt Anchor: where no tempeſt can annoy vs, or ſtorme how boiſterous ſoeuer trouble vs; where a gale of pleaſure ſhall blow continually vpon our ſailes; where the Sonne of righteouſneſſe ſhall be our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13835:36"/>
only Load-ſtarre, and the Father and Holy Ghoſt be <hi>&amp; Prora &amp; Puppis,</hi> all in all vnto vs: which God grant.</p>
            <p>But now, for that the holy Scriptures are indeed our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> liuely Oracles, teaching vs and all the ſeruants of God what vſe to make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this and any other the like cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie: let vs I beſeech you now draw neere to the ſame, and heare what the Lord ſpeaketh to his people out of a part of that Pſalme euen now ſung, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. <hi>verſe</hi> 11. The words are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When thou with rebukes doeſt chaſtiſe man for iniquitie, thou as a moth makeſt his beautie to conſume: ſurely euery man is vanitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which words taken generally, are no other then a plaine Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein our Prophet doth manifeſt to the world what God is; how great, how glorious; in power infinite, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie incomprehenſible: Things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed moſt neceſſary to be knowne in regard of God, that man may yeeld the greater obedience and reuerence vnto him, of whom naturally hee hath ſo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13835:36"/>
meane and ordinary thoughts; imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, if not worſe then himſelfe, (as thoſe Heathens doe <hi>Act.</hi> 17. <hi>gold and ſiluer</hi>) yet at the leaſtwiſe like vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as it is plaine <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21.</p>
            <p>Now that he that runneth may reade theſe things in God, therefore doth our Prophet demonſtrate and ſet forth this God, though not as God doth himſelfe elſewhere by his glorious name <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.14. and glorious workes,
<list>
                  <item>1. Of Creation, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.20.</item>
                  <item>2. Of Prouidence, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.24.</item>
               </list>
yet in as familiar a manner and way of compariſon, comparing him and man together. Man wee know of all other creatures here in this inferiour world is the moſt excellent, comming moſt neere to God,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> created after his owne image, in whoſe breaſt are hidden thoſe ſparkes of diuine nature a little lower then God:<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.6.</note> and a little world of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, being moſt valiant, hardie, and of noble ſpirit; before whom the beaſts of the earth tremble, and whoſe preſence the fowles of the heauen cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. If then our Prophet will needs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13835:37"/>
compare the Creator with the creature, with whom may he better doe it then with man? And if not with him, <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto will ye liken me, ſaith the Lord? Iſa</hi> 40.18.</p>
            <p>Neither are we indeed to imagine, as though our Prophet by this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his, had any minde at all to dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or blemiſh in the leaſt reſpect the glory and beauty of this Almightie God. Alas brethren, if hee had ſuch a thought (as farre be ſuch thoughts from vs) ſo to conceit this compariſon, doubtleſſe this will not doe it. What beauty trow you is in the ſillieſt worme, to blemiſh the glory of the mightieſt Prince? or what light is in a ſmall and fading ſparkle, to darken the luſtre of the glorious Sunne? Nay rather wee ought to know, that this compariſon here of our Prophet, doth ſerue moſt excellently (as it vſually falleth out when contraries are compared) to ſet forth the wonderfull difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and man; his power, and mans weakneſſe; his eternitie, and mans vanitie. That we may yet looke further
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13835:37"/>
into theſe things, let vs I beſeech you conſider in the <hi>Demonſtration</hi> theſe Two things
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The precedent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The ſubſequent.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Precedent</hi> in theſe words; <hi>when thou with &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Subſequent</hi> in theſe, <hi>Thou as a moth makeſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And withall let vs obſerue him lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe the ground of this latter; <hi>Surely</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>euery man is vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>precedent</hi> we are not to behold God ſleeping but waking: When a ſleepe no difference betweene the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and valiant man: the couragious Lyon and timerous Hare: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſetteth forth God, not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, but rouſing vp himſelfe: meaning indeed to ſhew himſelfe a God in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing man for his offences, and taking this courſe with him; then what followeth? the <hi>ſubſequent</hi> is, <hi>as a Moth, &amp;c.</hi> well put both together the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13835:38"/>
               <hi>precedent</hi> and <hi>ſubſequent,</hi> and then you haue the compariſon whereof I ſpake before, God compared to a fretting, deuouring Moth: and man to a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and delightfull garment: the Moth ſeaſeth vpon the garment, and the beautie of the garment preſently waſteth. <hi>God rebuketh man for his ſinne,</hi> and man withall his glory ſodainely va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth. And no maruell, <hi>for he is but vanitie.</hi> To ſee the compariſon a little better. A garment we know let it be of neuer ſo rich a cloth, or the thred neuer ſo purely ſpunne, let the die be <hi>Tirian</hi> or <hi>Babiloniſh,</hi> ſuch a garment as <hi>Achan</hi> purchaſed at ſo deare a rate, or <hi>Salomon</hi> wore vpon his Feſtiuall daies, a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherein Arte contended with Nature, and nature onely in her Lillie excelled Arte: yet no ſooner, doth the Moth take it but as ſodainely the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof fadeth. So ſaith our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet here: And the like ſaith <hi>Eliphaz, Iob</hi> 4.19. is man compared with God: make him therefore as great as you can, deſire, and happie with the happieſt: let Nature furniſh him with her richeſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13835:38"/>
ſtore, and Fortune ſeate him vpon the height of her wheele; let him haue riches, honour, wiſedome, ſtrength and what you will, yet if the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to rebuke this man for his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, theſe will not ſerue him: for no ſooner God chideth but the man with his beautie conſumeth; and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, for ſurely he is but vanitie.</p>
            <p>But yet more particularly in the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent</hi> wee are to take notice of theſe three things:
<list>
                  <item>1. That there is a time of rebuk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and chaſtening of man.</item>
                  <item>2. From whom thoſe rebukes and chaſtiſements doe proceed and come.</item>
                  <item>3. The reaſon of the ſame plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denoted:
<list>
                        <item>1. The firſt in theſe words <hi>when with rebukes, man chaſtened.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. The ſecond is expreſſed onely in this word, <hi>Thou; Thou doeſt chaſten man.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. The third and laſt is the very concluſion <hi>(for iniquity) when thou with rebuks doeſt chaſten man for iniquity.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:13835:39"/>The firſt of theſe that there is a time of rebuking and chaſtening of man: as it is an infallible truth ſo ſhall I not neede to ſpend the leaſt time in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and further prouing the ſame. If any doubt hereof I would deſire them to heare the Preacher ſpeaking out of the third of <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> and the firſt verſe, <hi>To all things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there is an appointed time.</hi> And the fourth verſe of the ſame Chapter, <hi>There is a time of weeping, a time of laughing, a time of mourning, a time of dauncing;</hi> Let them likewiſe heare what <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh in the 21. Chapter of his booke and 17. verſe <hi>How oft is the candle of the wicked lighted, and how often commeth their deſtruction vpon them?</hi> Noting as the former doth changes and alterations in mans eſtate: He flouriſheth for a time, but anone after he is rebuked, oft lighted and as oft extinguiſhed. Neither can they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede haue poſſibly a better Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtris then Experience herſelfe whoſe daily leſſon is, that there is no conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie at all to be expected in theſe <hi>ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie</hi> bodies, nothing here but <hi>viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:13835:39"/>
and alterations, ſometimes well, oftentimes ſicke, now rich, then poore; laſt day ſinging, this day ſorrowing: God giuing, and God taking away. This is that I ſay which not onely Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, but the holy Scripture prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally teacheth to be the portion both of the prophane man, as alſo of the deareſt ſeruants of God: neither is loue or hatred to be deſerued by it. And for the latter if time, would ſuffer vs to take a view of the liues of holy men, the holieſt that euer liued, we ſhould eaſily finde the truth thereof, their eſtate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not alwaies the ſame, but as they met ſome good daies, ſo they croſſed as many euill wherein were not onely<note n="*" place="margin">Preſſurae. Heb. 10.33.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>afflictions,</hi> but <hi>oppreſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which occaſioned <hi>Iacob</hi> in my minde to ſpeake as he did to <hi>Pharaoh Gen.</hi> 47.9. <hi>The daies of the yeeres of my pilgrimage are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>few and euill.</hi> Intimating not ſo few as euill; yea our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe was ſo broken and wounded for our tranſgreſſions, and the chaſticement of our peace ſo
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13835:40"/>
vpon him; a man of that daily ſorrow, that ſome take the ground of the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes</hi> ſpeech <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.57. <hi>Quinquaginta annos nondum habes: Thou art not yet fifty yeeres old:</hi> to be altogether from his looke and countenance ſo auncient and full of wrinkles, that although not fully 33. yet he looked as a man of fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Howſoeuer yet this muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie be yeelded as a truth, elſe had it beene a thing needleſſe and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous altogether for our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt to admoniſh his Diſciples as hee doth ſo oft,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.</note> both of the Bridegroomes departure from them,<note place="margin">Marc. 1.</note> and alſo of the taking vp of the Croſſe and daily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of him,<note place="margin">Luc. 5.</note> if there were not ſuch daies as theſe: daies of rebuke and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations to be expected, not onely of the bad but likewiſe of the good, and that all things herein come alike to both. The which being ſo, then let it not ſeeme ſtrange to any eſpecially to our ſelues that our wheele is thus in an inſtant turned, and our pleaſant ſpring ſtrangely changed: that after ſo faire a calme wee are beaten with ſo ſoare a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13835:40"/>
tempeſt, knowing that this is the time of our chaſticement.</p>
            <p>Hetherto was our Summer, and we are they alone that feele this winter. Howbeit in truth we are not alone: For neither doe we ſuffer alone as the onely perſons that haue ſeene affliction (no alas wee doe but ſippe of that cuppe whereof ſo many holy men Patriarkes,<note place="margin">Lam. 12.3.</note> Prophets, and bleſſed Martyrs haue drunke ſo large a draught,) neither do we ſorrow alone; for whilſt wee weepe there are thoſe that weepe with vs: and whilſt we lament behold how a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber on all hands doe ſympathize <hi>Sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men miſeris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in the <hi>precedent</hi> is the Authour of theſe rebukes, namely, from whom they doe proceede, and come: the which is expreſſed in the word <hi>Thou,</hi> ſomewhat darkely I muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, yet afterward in the 12. verſe of this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> more plainely and cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for there he ſtileth him by the name of Lord <hi>(Heare my praier O Lord)</hi> ſo here <hi>when thou</hi> (that is) that mightie
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13835:41"/>
God hauing a being in thy ſelfe, doeſt giue a ſubſiſtance and being to afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and chaſticements: Intimating that from him is <hi>Malum poenae</hi> as for vs <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum culpae,</hi> the euill of puniſhment, though not euill of ſinne. Thus God ſpeaketh of himſelfe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.7. <hi>I forme the light and create darkeneſſe, I make peace and create euill.</hi> And as the euill ſo the euill Doer, as he further ſpeaketh in the ſame propheſie, cap. 54.16. <hi>I haue created the Smith that bloweth in the fire, and I haue created the Deſtroier to deſtroy.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Amos</hi> taketh it as granted in the third Chapter of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie and the third verſe <hi>That there is no euill in the Citie that the Lord hath not done.</hi> And this verily hath alwaies been the concluſion of the ſeruants of God, at all times, and in all ages, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer afflictions they haue met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in this their pilgrimage that the ſame came from God. Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> when <hi>Shemei</hi> curſed him with an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible curſe, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.5. concluded that God had hidden him and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none muſt touch him. Thus <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:13835:41"/>
long before <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10.3. when his ſonnes were ſtriken dead before the Lord, held his peace, concluding it was the Lord that would be ſanctified of all, that come neere him. This laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was the concluſion of the whole Church in generall; when as manifold afflictions like a darke cloud wrapt her in on euery ſide, <hi>Lament.</hi> 2.17. <hi>The Lord hath done</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>that which he purpoſed, he hath fulfilled that which hee determined.</hi> A truth moſt neceſſarie to be knowne in theſe two reſpects.</p>
            <p>The firſt is to comfort and incourage the ſeruants of God, and vs eſpecially to beare and vndergo, all croſſes and calamities how bitter ſo euer, with the greater patience, and cheerefulneſſe, conſidering they come from him who as a Father to all, ſo is he principally to the elect, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.16. An earthly father wee know may at his pleaſure and as he ſeeth iuſt cauſe, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and correct his childe, neither ought the childe to take it otherwiſe then well, in no cauſe either murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or reſiſting: and if an earthly, then
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13835:42"/>
much more (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.) may the Father of Spirits, our heauenly, and we in the meane while receiuing the ſame moſt patiently and contentedly. <hi>Iſaackes</hi> burthen <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 12.6. was both heauie and vncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; heauie for the matter, vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable for the end: And yet as farre as we can read he bare it willingly, the reaſon I take it is expreſſed in the ſame verſe, <hi>Pater impoſuit, His Father laid it on him.</hi> Whoſe example my deſire is may be ours: What God will haue let vs imbrace: if hee will impoſe it let vs indure it: remembring the counſell of <hi>Salomon</hi> to his ſonne, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.11. <hi>My ſon refuſe not the chaſticing of the Lord, for whom hee loueth hee correcteth.</hi> Who knoweth not that the Argument that <hi>Abſolom</hi> vſed to perſwade his Siſter <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> to patience,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 13.20.</note> bearing as ſhe might, the hard dealing of her brother with her, was but onely this <hi>Frater eſt, He is thy Brother?</hi> doubtleſſe if this were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as he thought ſufficient to ſtill her voice, that then cried and wept ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, and pacifie her wrath and furie
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13835:42"/>
againſt him, that ſo iuſtly had deſerued it. Then Brethren I beſeech you, how much more ought the conſideration of the perſon, from whom, this calamitie is thus ſodainely come (he indeed our gratious Father) to perſwade, and put vs on, to indure the ſame, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented mindes: knowing withall, Firſt, that as he neuer offended vs, ſo haue we infinitely him. And ſecondly that it is come from that ſweet hand, from whom we haue all our liues long, euen to this inſtant, receiued ſuch a world of bleſſings: receiuing then ſo many good things, is it not reaſon, that wee ſhould receiue ſome euill?</p>
            <p>Secondly, this doth afford vnto vs a moſt neceſſarie direction, to whom to reſort, in this and all other our greateſt miſeries, ſurely to him onely, and to no other. Intimating herein, the poore Prodigall, who being in that miſery, wherein he was, would trie the curteſie of no more Citizens, but went ſtraight way to his Father; <hi>I will</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>go to my Father,</hi> ſo let vs to ours. Thus doe the ſeruants of God hearten on,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13835:43"/>
and incourage each other in their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt trialls.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>Come</hi> (ſay they) <hi>let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the Lord he hath ſpoiled and will heale vs, he hath wounded and hee will binde vs vp.</hi> Neither ought we to bee diſcouraged in ſo doing, ſeeing this is he whoſe name,<note place="margin">Pro. 18.10</note> is <hi>a ſtrong Tower</hi> to which the righteous flie (flying doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vpon the wings of their faith) and are exalted.<note place="margin">Ier. 31.20.</note> This is our mercifull Father, who whilſt he is ſtriking hath his bowels ſore troubled and his <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance rolled vpon him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.8.</note> For a little ſpace I confeſſe he hath beene angrie, but if we ſeeke him in due time he will yet be found of vs,<note place="margin">Iſa. 54.7.9.</note> yea he will returne with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of compaſſion.<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.6.</note> Let the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians</hi> therefore in the time of danger tie and binde their <hi>Mars</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them with gyues and fetters of gold. And let vs onely hold and tie God, with teares and praiers; Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Iacob</hi> who although the principall <hi>ſinnewes</hi> were ſhrunke in his thigh, yet would he not ſuffer,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.26.</note> the Angell to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part without a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt thing that we are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13835:43"/>
to conſider in the <hi>precedent</hi> is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why man is rebuked, conteined as we heard in this word <hi>Iniquitie, when thou with rebuke doeſt chaſtice man for iniquitie:</hi> Now iniquity we are to know is, taken diuerſly in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: two waies eſpecially, either for ſome great and hainous ſinne: and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, doe the brethren of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſpeake to him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 44.6. <hi>God hath found out the iniquitie of his ſeruants,</hi> that is their great and heinous ſinne, and is now ready to puniſh them.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, for ſinne in generall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to that <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. <hi>The wrath of God is reuealed from heauen againſt all iniquity:</hi> And ſo in this place for iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is for the ſinne. Now ſinne is tearmed by the name of Iniquity <hi>Quia peccatum eſt ab aequitate alienum,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtles owne expreſſion <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.4. <hi>For ſin is the tranſgreſſion of Law.</hi> Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or ſinne is nothing elſe but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a tranſgreſſion or croſſing of the Law of God. And indeed <hi>hinc lachrymae,</hi> hence it is (ſaith our Prophet)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13835:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that man is rebuked: ſuteable to that <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.39. <hi>Wherefore then is the liuing man ſorrowfull? man ſuffereth for his ſinne.</hi> With which agreeth the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Stipendia peccati mors: The wages of ſinne is death:</hi> that is not onely the reaſon why ſoule and body be ſeparated, and nature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied, but the cauſe likewiſe of all that labour and trauell to which man is daily ſubiect as the ſparkes to mount vpwards,<note place="margin">Iob. 15.7.</note> 
               <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.7. Iniquitie I know right well, is not alwaies the chiefe cauſe of Gods rebukes, and chaſtice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; yet is it vſually found in ſuch as are rebuked and corrected. Let <hi>Iob</hi> I pray you be our example: (neither indeed doe I remember any one more pregnant) whoſe trialls as all know were exceeding great (take his owne word) heauier then the ſand of the ſea, <hi>Iob</hi> 6.3. and yet the end that the Lord propounded, as the euent ſhewed, was not ſimply to rebuke him for his ſinne, but rather in ſo doing to trie his faith and patience, and accordingly to leaue him a Mirror of both, to ſucceeding
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13835:44"/>
ages. <hi>Iames</hi> 5.11. notwithſtanding conſider but the paſſage of things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and him, and him and his friends, and you ſhall finde matter ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, as for that, ſo a farre greater hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, as he freely acknowledgeth vnto God crying <hi>peccaui,</hi> Chap. 42. 5. 6. Neither are wee indeed to haue the leaſt thought of iniuſtice or cruelty in God in thus puniſhing man for his iniquitie: For ſhall not the Iudge of the world doe right? <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.14. No bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſinne is another matter, and of farre greater conſequent, then the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſon and prophane imagineth.</p>
            <p>For firſt of all iniquity or ſinne is a croſſing as we heard before and thwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Law of God:<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.7. Rom. 2.1.13.14. Iſa. 6.3.</note> A law firſt of all perfect in it ſelfe, and drawing men on more and more to perfection. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly a Law, of an infinite God and therefore carying with it an infinite puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſinne as it is contrarie to the Law, ſo to the Law-giuer himſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.1. Coloſſ. 1.15.</note> He being light, and that darkneſſe: He pure and that filthy: He ſpirituall
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13835:45"/>
and aboue, that carnall and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, it is that which defaceth the image of God in man, and like another bewitching <hi>Delila,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.9. Leuit. 11.44. Mar. 7.23.</note> hauing inſnared the vnhappy wretch, neuer gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him ouer til thoſe beautifull locks of his (the ornaments I meane of his minde) be quite ſhred off,<note place="margin">2 Cor 5.27</note> the light of his vnderſtanding darkened, (if not quite extinguiſhed) and he of a Prince made a priſoner,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.5.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.7. Eph. 4.24.</note> of a great Lord a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſlaue, not to a few, but to all, euen his meaneſt and baſeſt enemies. Sinne being then (as wee heare) the cauſe vſually why man is rebuked, then ought we in the firſt place to be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly thankfull to God, that for all our ſinnes he hath ſo long ſpared vs, yea the time of our rebuking being come, is it not his great mercy, that whileſt the beſt is thus corrected, the worſt are not conſumed? <hi>Lament.</hi> 3. And in the next place how ought this likewiſe to ſettle our mindes further patiently to endure the rod of God, diuerting all our thoughts wholly from him to our
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13835:45"/>
ſelues, making vs impatient with none, but with our ſinnes indeed occaſioning all this? <hi>Abner</hi> we ſee for a time dalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but ere <hi>Aſahel</hi> is aware, with the hinder end of his ſpeare hee ſtriketh: And this <hi>Egyptian robber,</hi> howſoeuer ſhe embraceth, yet if ſhe can at the laſt ſhe ſtrangleth.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſinne being (as wee heare) thus hatefull in the ſight of God, then you that loue the Lord, hate euill, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.10. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.15.</p>
            <p>Hate it: Firſt, as an enemie to God. What the Father iuſtly hateth, there is no reaſon in the world that the ſonne ſhould loue. Our Father long agoe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne the <hi>Feud:</hi> let vs I beſeech you his ſonnes and daughters continue it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as an enemie to our ſelues, it being the originall not onely of this, (as before was ſhewed) but of all other miſeries and calamities that wee meet withall here in this troubleſome vale: euery day that hath the leaſt, hauing by meanes thereof enough of the owne ſorrow.</p>
            <p>And therefore howſoeuer the foole
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13835:46"/>
maketh a ſport of ſinne, <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 10.23. and 14.9. let vs I pray you, foſter no ſuch Scorpion in our boſomes, which howſoeuer (as I ſaid before) it may fawne for a time, will at the laſt wound vs to the heart: whoſe pleaſures are but for a ſeaſon,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25</note> and their end alwayes bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſubſequent</hi> are in theſe words: <hi>As a moth thou makeſt his beauty to conſume.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which words haue diuers ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications allowed them by Interpreters. We will thinke only but of two: And firſt of all they are taken
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Paſſiuely.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Actiuely.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſiuely, that a man, howſoeuer he may preſume perhaps vpon himſelfe, his ſtrength, wiſdome, riches, and many other preferments, yet is he no more in the hand of God, then the ſillieſt moth in the hands of the mightieſt man, who at his pleaſure cruſheth the ſame, and bringeth it vnto nothing. The which indeed is a truth, and the onely drift of our Prophet here in this place, to ſhew the vanitie of man; howbeit, the ſame
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13835:46"/>
to my thinking expreſſed after another manner: And therefore we will follow the ſecond opinion, taking our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets meaning altogether <hi>Actiuely,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending a compariſon, wherein God is (as wee heard before) compared to a moth, and man to a garment: The which compariſon or ſimilitude of his he rather (in my iudgement) chuſeth then any other, not only in regard of the ſecret and ſudden working of God in humbling and abaſing of the prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt man, but alſo as beſt ſuiting the prophane, and yet ordinary conceit that man hath of the eternall and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, eſteeming him no better then a moth or flie, and his anger but a buzz, and not to be regarded. An hard cenſure I muſt needs confeſſe of the creature, eſpecially in regard of the Creator; yet our Prophet ſeemeth to yeeld to what they affirme: <hi>A moth,</hi> ſaith he, but withall ſheweth, that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a moth, yet a dreadfull one, as ſoone ſpoiling and conſuming the mightieſt Potentate, and moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perſon in the world, together with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13835:47"/>
all his glory and beauty, as the moth doth the faireſt garment and of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt luſtre. Now although that this compariſon here vſed by our Prophet, be ſufficient of it ſelfe to ſet forth God euen in his weakneſſe, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.15. farre ſtronger then man; yet for the vnderſtanding of the words the better, we are to conſider the reaſon of either.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, why God as a moth conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, why man ſo glorious a creature is ſo ſuddenly conſumed as a garment.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of the former, wee ſhall finde the better, if we conſider the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God here likened to a moth, ſet forth vnto vs in the holy Scriptures by other compariſons farre more honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as namely <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.8. by <hi>A Beare robbed of her whelpes, rending and tearing the heart and call. Ioel</hi> 3.6. by <hi>a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lion roaring out of Sion, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and earth ſhaking.</hi> But of all others, moſt glorious are thoſe compariſons that you may reade of <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9.10.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13835:47"/>
where he is deſcribed, hauing <hi>His haires as pure wooll, and his eyes a flaming fire: A fiery ſtreame going before him, and thouſand thouſands miniſtring vnto him. Iob</hi> 15.10. <hi>Beholding the heauens, and they are impure in his ſight.</hi> And <hi>Iob</hi> 4.18. <hi>Imputing follie to his Angels. Iſa.</hi> 44.13. <hi>Crying and ſhouting like a man of warre. Ioſ.</hi> 5.13. <hi>A valiant Captaine with a glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering ſword in his hand. Apoc.</hi> 19.13.16. <hi>His Coat-armour dipt in bloud, whereupon is written</hi> (without doubt in golden let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) <hi>Rex regum, &amp; Dominus dominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, The King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi> But of all other, that <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29. <hi>For our God is a conſuming fire.</hi> No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell then if whileſt hee rebuketh, the beauty of man conſumeth. <hi>For this is he that toucheth the mountaines, and they ſmoake; and at whoſe rebuke the ancient hills vaniſh.</hi> Now the only reaſon why the ſpirit of God both here and in ſo many other places in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſo frequent in deſcribing and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth of this God, is without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (as wee haue heard before) that man, ſillie man, may haue more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13835:48"/>
thoughts, together with a more high and reuerend eſteeme of the diuine and glorious maieſtie, then na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turally hee hath. For certainly the thoughts of man in regard of God are (as I ſaid) moſt ordinary and meane, as may appeare
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>By the Honour,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>By the Feare,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
(though both his due) that are vſually affoorded vnto him.</p>
            <p>And firſt for honour, there is no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but that honour is due to him, not only as the Father of vs all, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.6. and accordingly doth he challenge it to himſelfe of all his ſonnes and daughters <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>If I be a Father, where is mine honour?</hi> but alſo it is his due, as our dread Soueraigne, and King vniuerſall: which maketh our Prophet <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.11. ſo earneſtly to exhort all ſorts, yea the moſt puiſſant Princes on the earth, to doe their homage daily before him for feare of his high diſpleaſure. Now how farre men are from the performance of this ſo neceſſary a dutie, may appeare,</p>
            <p>Firſt, by the obedience that is yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13835:48"/>
to his moſt bleſſed word,<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.2 Iſa. 53.1.</note> 
               <hi>That rod of his power,</hi> whereby hee ruleth in the middeſt of his enemies. Who (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) like <hi>Eſter</hi> toucheth this Mighties Scepter, and boweth himſelfe before it? Nay doe not men rather imbaſe and contemne the ſame? he ſaying what he will, and they notwithſtanding doing what they liſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, who doth honour this God as he ought, in deuoting to him all that he hath, ſoule and body,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>a hauing Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> making his members weapons of righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.7.</note> and daily opening the doores of that faire Temple of his, (his ſoule I meane) that ſo <hi>the Sonne of glory may come in,</hi> and not onely inlighten, but inrich the ſame with all ſauing gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Faith, Hope, Repentance, Peace of conſcience, Sanctification,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.21.</note> and ſuch like?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, who doth honour him in depending and waiting vpon his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence both in proſperitie and alſo in aduerſitie?</p>
            <p>In proſperitie neither ſacrificing to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> his net,<note place="margin">Hab. 1.16.</note> nor burning incenſe to his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13835:49"/>
yarne, but with <hi>Iacob Gen.</hi> 32.10. aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing all that he hath, his whole eſtate, to God the giuer of euery good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> gift.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> Being full, not forgetting him whoſe ſtepe haue thus dropt downe fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon him,<note place="margin">Deut. 8.14 Pſal. 65.11 Iob. 21.3. &amp; 29.2.</note> and whoſe light now ſhineth vpon his habitation.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, in aduerſitie is not ready with prophane <hi>Eſau</hi> to ſell his birthright,<note place="margin">Gen. 25.34.</note> as occaſion ſerueth, to free and deliuer himſelfe from the correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand of God, vnder which he ought rather to humble himſelfe, with that holy mans reſolution; <hi>Although thou killeſt me, yet will I truſt in thee. Iob</hi> 13.15.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the feare of God, it is that which the Lord himſelfe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and challengeth likewiſe at the hands of all his ſeruants.<note place="margin">Ier. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>Deut</hi> 4.9. and 6.2. <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28. And yet who is there that feareth this God with that awfull reuerence that is due to him? No (alas) men feare the creature more then the Creator, the garment more then the maker. Earthly men are feared, eſpecially Kings and Princes of the earth, and good reaſon, for their wrath
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13835:49"/>
is the meſſenger of death:<note place="margin">Pro. 16.14.</note> If men feare them, then who would not much more feare thee, <hi>Oh King of Nations?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 10.7.</note> But the truth is,<note place="margin">Gen. 20.11.</note> there is little feare of God at this time (I will not ſay with <hi>Abraham, in this place,</hi> for farre be it from me by ſo ſaying to wrong ſo Chriſtian an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie, howbeit this I may ſafely ſay) in ſome parts of the Land. Inſtances let me giue you two. Firſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.6.</note> doe not men ordinarily thoſe things that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences doe tell them vex and grieue our gratious Father as he fitteth in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen?<note place="margin">Eph. 4.30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, are not things vſually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the flaming eye of God,<note place="margin">Dan. 10.6. Ioſ. 7.21.</note> which men labour by all meanes poſſible to cloake and couer from the knowledge of the world? Certainly, where theſe things are, there is no feare of God, and if it be, ſure I am no filiall. And ſeeing it is ſo, how neceſſary then is it for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of vs to haue this God alwayes before our eyes, not only as he is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in his moſt holy word, but verify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth thereof both in rewarding of the righteous,<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.10 Rom. 2.6.</note> and puniſhing of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13835:50"/>
wicked,<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.12.</note> giuing euery man according to his workes? Let the kindneſſe of God allure vs, and his mercies ſhowring daily vpon the dwellings of the righteous, perſwade vs to honour and feare this Almighty God.</p>
            <p>If not they, then let the Maieſtie of God ſtrike a terrour into vs, wee ſeeing this deuouring moth ſuddenly conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the beauty euen of the mightieſt, in the middeſt of all their royaltie. Let vs therefore behold <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the middeſt of his Armie drowning,<note place="margin">Exo. 14.20 Dan. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſhazer</hi> in the middeſt of his cups trembling,<note place="margin">2. King. 19.37. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Sanacharib</hi> in the middeſt of his Temple dying, and his Epitaph ouer him warning all men to feare this dreadfull moth. Laſtly, let vs behold black-mouthed <hi>Iulian,</hi> in the middeſt of his greateſt ſecuritie breathing out his damned ſpirit with <hi>Viciſti Galilae.</hi> Thus I ſay let vs take notice of the goodneſſe of this God, as alſo of his almightie power, by opening our eares to his voice, and our eyes to his workes: ſo ſhall we thinke moſt highly of him, and baſely of our ſelues; honour him, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13835:50"/>
humble our ſelues, ſaying with <hi>Iob, I haue heard of thee by the hearing, but now mine eye ſeeth thee, therefore I abhorre my ſelfe in duſt and aſhes, Iob</hi> 42.4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let vs (I pray you) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as before the power of the moth, ſo in the laſt place the frailtie of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: a principall ground or reaſon why it is ſo ſuddenly conſumed. <hi>Surely euery man is vanitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which being a principle hardly beleeued, is therefore (as you ſee) by our Prophet earneſtly vrged &amp; preſſed. <hi>Surely</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>man,</hi> that is, not one man, but all, not this man, but euery man, <hi>is vanitie.</hi> Further, whereas hee ſaith <hi>man,</hi> we muſt not take him alone, but attended likewiſe with all his glory, the garment with the beautie, and both but vanitie.</p>
            <p>Let vs (I pray you) ſingle out both theſe, that ſo wee may take the better notice of either.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the glory and beauty of man in the firſt place, being no other but the poſſeſſion of thoſe things, as we heard before, that make him glorious
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13835:51"/>
and renowned, as honour, riches, ſtrength, beautie, and the like: all which he ſheweth to be no better then man, and man vanitie.</p>
            <p>And indeed vanitie they are, Firſt in themſelues, being moſt vnconſtant and vncertaine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in their promiſes, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing much, but performing little, nay for the moſt part the quite contrary happening.</p>
            <p>Their manner is to make men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that they can lengthen out their dayes, but alas oftentimes they ſhorten them; that they can make them the happieſt vnder the Sunne, and for the moſt part they make them the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, not only in bringing with them ſuch a number of cares and troubles, but alſo ſo locking vp and impriſoning their thoughts in themſelues, that their ſoules haue no libertie, ſcarce an houre in a yeere, to conſider of thoſe things, wherein the true ioy and comfort of a Chriſtian conſiſteth: for which their falſe and deceitfull dealing, they haue the lie giuen them <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.2. And the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13835:51"/>
Prophet <hi>Ierem.</hi> 9.23.24. exhorteth all thoſe that haue them, in no caſe to be ouer-ioyed or puffed vp with them. <hi>Let not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the wiſe man reioyce in his wiſdome, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtrength, neither the rich man in his riches: But if any glory, let him in this, that hee knoweth me that ſheweth mercy and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as his glory is, ſo is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nothing better, but vanitie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, vanitie, being taken from ſo fraile and brittle an element.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, vanitie, being ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect euery moment to be diſſolued into the ſame againe, and in the meane while meeting with ſuch and ſo many ſorrowes, and with ſo few and ſuch mixed pleaſures, that leauing the ſtage, hee may cloſe vp his part with that ſpeech of <hi>Iob,</hi> 4. <hi>I had for inheritance the moneths of vanitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then that man with all his glory is vanitie, let vs not then (I pray you) build vpon him in the leaſt regard placing our truſt and confidence in him, <hi>No</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> 46.3.) <hi>not in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13835:52"/>
Princes.</hi> One reaſon is there: <hi>for there is no helpe in them.</hi> There is another, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.22. <hi>for their breath is in their noſtrils.</hi> And here in my text the ground of both: <hi>For they are but vanitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as we build not vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo let vs not (I pray you) build vpon our ſelues in regard of any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward priuilege whatſoeuer, ſeeing wee are no better then others, but euen va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie as well as they.</p>
            <p>But here let me make a ſtay a little, and propound two queſtions, which being anſwered, then will I draw to a concluſion.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſhall be this, What the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould be, that God being ſo ſtrong and man ſo weake, the wicked notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, ſhould liue, and wax old, and grow in wealth, <hi>Iob</hi> 2.7. Theſe are Gods enemies, why doth hee then ſuffer them, ſeeing if he pleaſe he can ſo ſuddenly conſume them?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that long life, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the fruition and enioyment of theſe outward things, are not alwayes a bleſſing, and if they be; ſurely rather
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13835:52"/>
               <hi>Eſaus,</hi> yea euen in <hi>Eſaus</hi> eye they are not the beſt, which maketh him ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented with his brother for leauing him but only this. And in truth God ſuffereth the wicked oft times as <hi>Dauid</hi> did both <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Adonijah</hi> from their cradle, laying the raynes vpon their necks, and giuing them their hearts deſire: his rod is not vpon them,<note place="margin">Iob 21.7.8.9.</note> they ſpend their dayes in eaſe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and all this in the end for their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. Such lenitie as this in man is cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in God ſeueritie. A ſore puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that God oft times inflicteth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the worſt men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.29.</note> in giuing them vp to their hearts deſire. The foole hath his eaſe, and this ſlaieth him.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly there are diuers other ſpeciall ends that our heauenly Father propoundeth to himſelfe in all this. I will name but ſome of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to allure and draw the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> man to repentance:<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>knoweſt thou that the patience, and long ſuffering, and beautifulneſſe of the Lord, leadeth thee to repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, that <hi>Aſher</hi> may be the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:13835:53"/>
rodde of his wrath and ſtaffe of his indignation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.51. to ſcourge and humble his Church, and people for their iniquities.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, to take away in the end all excuſe from them: <hi>That thou mighteſt be iuſtified when thou ſpeakeſt, and cleare when thou iudgeſt, Pſal.</hi> 50.4.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And laſtly, to ſhew vnto the world, that the happineſſe of a Chriſtian, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth not in theſe outward and fading things; but that there is another recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.26</note> to which <hi>Moſes</hi> and all the faithfull haue from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning looked, of higher nature, and more noble conſequence.</p>
            <p>My ſecond demaund ſhall be, the reaſon, why the Lord thus ſparing the wicked man and miſcreant, doth in the meane time rebuke and chaſtice his deareſt ſeruants, and oft-times, in this very kinde cutting them off in their flouriſhing age?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.22</note>Now the Reſolution in a word, that not onely afflictions, but death it ſelfe is to the ſeruants of God great aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:13835:53"/>And firſt for afflictions, they ſerue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> moſt excellently to weare and waſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by little and little that body of death or rather ſinne, that is the cauſe of death, and whereof the Apoſtle ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly complaineth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. Theſe are the refining pot,<note place="margin">Eze. 22.20. Pro. 17.3.</note> of the Lord whereby he purgeth his gold from the droſſe; and his cutting knife, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he cleanſeth his vine,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.1.</note> and is daily pruning of the ſuperfluous branches.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to weane them more and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> more from this world, that with the <hi>Epicures</hi> they ſhould not make their neſt, hereupon the earth: or with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> delight too much in this their <hi>Egypt,</hi> but that loathing the Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 120.5</note> they ſhould long hourely for the habitation of <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, To make the kingdome of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> heauen (they being once entred the ſame) the more pleaſant and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to them. The poore Pilgrime that hath now beene deteined ſometime in forraine parts farre from his natiue ſoile, the worſe his condition hath beene, the more welcome is his home
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13835:54"/>
vnto him? with what cheere doth hee enter his doores; and with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment doth he ſit him downe in the middeſt of his friends flocking on all hands to congratulate his returne? His miſery paſt is inſtantly forgotten; or if he ſpeaketh of it at any time, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with much delight. Doubtleſſe this is the eſtate, of all the ſeruants of God their pilgrimage once ended, and they through manifold afflictions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred that bleſſed Pallace, by how much they haue more ſuffered, by ſo much are their ioyes more augmented. Here they were contemned and ſpurned at: How comfortable then are the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracings of that heauenly company vnto them? Here naked or at the leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in ragges and patches. How wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come then are thoſe pure garments the pretious robes of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to them? Here hungrie and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty.<note place="margin">Apoc. 7.9.</note> How happy then doe they thinke themſelues, being once ſet at Table with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſonnes,<note place="margin">Mark. 8.</note> feaſting and banqueting in the kingdome of God?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:13835:54"/>Laſtly, hereby thoſe graces, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would lie hid and buried within them (or at leaſtwiſe not ſhew themſelues ſo clearely) are diſcouered and made manifeſt to the world. Theſe being the ſharpe and cutting windes of the Lord that blowing vpon his garden, cauſe theſe bleſſed flowers to caſt forth their ſauour. They bring indeed dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with them, but onely to this end that the beautie of theſe pretious Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondes may be the better veiwed and more plainely diſcerned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as theſe ſo death it ſelfe is gaine vnto them, die they ſooner or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; If later, then they are Schollers, longer trained vp in the Schoole of Chriſt, and hauing greater experience of the goodneſſe of God, attaine to an higher pitch in grace and fuller ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if Chriſt calleth ſooner, the ſooner doth <hi>Bartimeus</hi> throw off his patched cloake. And the ſooner the Angell calleth <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſooner doth he leaue that ſtinking priſon of his; and through the iron gate entreth a Cittie
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13835:55"/>
both ſpatious and delightfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daughters of Ieruſalem</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) <hi>weepe not for mee,</hi> but <hi>weepe for your ſelues.</hi> And yet hee was then approaching the gates of death in the middeſt of his daies, and flower of his age, yet ſaith he <hi>Weepe not for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truely, no cauſe at all, had they to weepe for him, for now was the time, when the ſonne of man, ſhould bee glorified: Now was he to put off that ſhape, and forme of a ſeruant, which for our ſakes he had taken vpon him. <hi>Phil.</hi> 21.6.7. now was the time come, when being wholly freed from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and ſcorning of all his enemies, he ſhould be aduanced aboue all prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and powers, <hi>That at the name of Ieſus euery knee ſhould bow, Epheſ.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Phil.</hi> 21.10.</p>
            <p>Let them therefore not weepe for him, if they will weepe, then let them onely for themſelues and for their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And as this is the eſtate of the head, ſo is it likewiſe of the members: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the ignorant man eſteemeth
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13835:55"/>
them dying in the beſt of their ſtrength and middeſt of their daies, as vnhappy men; yet wee are to know, that this their taking away doth adde greatly to their happineſſe. For behold death giueth to them A <hi>quietus eſt</hi> from all their labours, and a ceſſation from all their troubles. After that no more paine or griefe, no more ſorrowing or lamenting:<note place="margin">Apoc. 7. &amp; 21.</note> 
               <hi>Their mouthes are filled with laughter; and the ſalt teares wiped from their eies.</hi> That pleaſant Land and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Hill, <hi>Mount Sion</hi> (I meane) which all their life long like <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſtanding on Mount <hi>Nebo</hi> they beheld afarre of, now they cheerefully enioy: here they walke to and fro, no longer by faith, but now by ſight they ſee as they are ſeene, they know as they are knowne. If then their eſtate be thus (as indeed it is,) and farre more happie a great deale then I am able to expreſſe) why ſhould any trouble themſelues in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing and lamenting the ſame which is euery way ſo bleſſed?</p>
            <p>But will one ſay to me; <hi>Not ſorrow?</hi> why who can with drie eies behold ſuch
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13835:56"/>
worthy perſons as this cut off in the prime of their age? who for their piety, wiſedome, learning, and many a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertue might haue ſtood the world (if God had thought ſo good) in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſteed. <hi>Shall the righteous periſh, and no man lay it to heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwere, though there bee no cauſe at all why we ſhould ſorrow for them, yet there is cauſe ſufficient for our ſelues: and that in theſe three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That when wee had them wee made no more accompt of them, not knowing our good vntill wee had loſt it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that by our ſinnes wee prouoked the Lord to depriue of ſo great comfort and to extinguiſh ſuch glorious lights in this Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let vs weepe for our ſelues, in that the euill day is ſo faſt approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon vs <hi>Theſe ſummer birds doe leaue vs, doubtleſſe:</hi> our winter is comming God haſteneth ſo faſt, his ſeruants into their chambers, and therefore we haue cauſe to feare that a ſtorme is at hand.<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.20.</note>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:13835:56"/>
But ſuppoſe the Lord ſpareth the Land in generall, yet good cauſe haue wee euery one in particular, to looke to himſelfe, wee heare what our Prophet heare affirmeth in the latter part of my Text, that <hi>Euery man is vanitie:</hi> and wofull experience this day verifieth the truth both of this, as alſo of the former: That when God rebuketh, man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth; and therefore it being ſo, let me deſire you all, a great aſſemblie here met together, (ſome I know onely <hi>to ſee, but moſt to ſorrow.</hi>) well to conſider the ſpeech of the Preacher, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.2. affirming that it is farre better to goe to ſuch a houſe as this, <hi>The houſe of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then the houſe of feaſting;</hi> and his reaſon is for this ſaith he is the end of all men, and the liuing will lay it to his heart. Giuing vs to vnderſtand, that ſuch places as this (where are ſo dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obiects offering themſelues to all) ſerue moſt excellently to awaken the drowſie and ſecure heart of man dreaming (as before) of I know not what perpetuity and ſtedfaſtneſſe of things here below; to entertaine
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13835:57"/>
thoughts farre differing, both of the vanitie and vncertainetie of all other things, ſo principally of man himſelfe. And accordingly I beſeech you let the temper of our thoughts be, wee are the liuing, in this honourable Gentleman, let vs behold the inconſtancie of all things here in this tranſitory world; and in his end, the end of vs all: and let vs not onely ſee but conſider, and lay it to our heart: where hee is now, we muſt all come hereafter, death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hauen, where the ſmalleſt boate, and talleſt ſhippe at the laſt arriueth: Yea the appointed Harbour of all the liuing, <hi>Iob.</hi> 30.30. we ſhall go to him, but he ſhall not returne to vs, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as he is gone before, and wee there is no remedie muſt follow after, ſo indeed know we not how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely, a hint whereof, our Prophet giueth in the firſt word of my Text. <hi>When thou,</hi> that is, at what time ſoeuer thou intendeſt to <hi>rebuke man:</hi> intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that as there is a day and time of rebuking, ſo God knoweth when, it
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13835:57"/>
may be neerer, it may be further off, it may be to morrow, it may be this night. <hi>Thou foole, he will take away thy ſoule from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure we are, we all muſt die, <hi>Old men may young men muſt:</hi> but who knoweth amongſt vs all, whoſe lot is next, and at whoſe doore the ſtaffe now ſtandeth? Seeing therefore it is ſo, let the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon, whoſe eyes the God of the world hath blinded, doe as pleaſeth him: let him make his reſt here on the earth, and minde no other but theſe earthly things: let his thoughts be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually working how to pull downe his barnes, and build bigger, or how he may goe to this or that Citie, and there continue a yeere to buy and ſell:<note place="margin">Iam. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>putting the euill day from him:</hi> Like thoſe whereof <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.12 calling for wine and ſtrong drinke, <hi>Come fetch wine, and let vs fill our ſelues with ſtrong drinke, for to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morrow ſhall be as this day and more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</hi> But let vs brethren take a quite contrarie courſe, ſeeing our liues are ſo vncertaine, to thinke more of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture then euer before: practiſing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13835:58"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:13835:58"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:13835:59"/>
the commaundement of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.41. <hi>Wake therefore, for you know not at what houre your Maſter will come.</hi> Getting into our Lampes ſtore of oyle, that ſo when the voice is <hi>Ecce ſponſus venit: Behold the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome commeth:</hi> we may likewiſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines be euery way fitted, to attend vpon him into that preſence Chamber whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this worthy perſon is already gone. To which moſt ſacred place, Chriſt for his mercies ſake bring vs all: to whom with the Father and the holy Spirit, be praiſe and glory world without end: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13835:59"/>
            <head>VPON THE FVNERALL of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> EDW. LEWKENOR.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>(1)</head>
               <l>AMongst the mournfull multitude which ſtand</l>
               <l>With Cypreſſe branches 'bout the monument</l>
               <l>Of this dead Knight, who liſt to vnderſtand</l>
               <l>His life, his death, what he, what his deſcent,</l>
               <l>With all which vnto him is pertinent:</l>
               <l>Right glad would I this gentle taske fulfill,</l>
               <l>But that my <hi>Muſe</hi> fearing it mought be ſhent</l>
               <l>For vndertaking thing beyond her skill,</l>
               <l>Only a Porters place will here ſupplie,</l>
               <l>To let them in, where they may read this hiſtorie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>(2)</head>
               <l>There they ſhall read, how worſhipfull his Berth,</l>
               <l>(To which ambitiouſly all ſorts aſpire,</l>
               <l>How e're in other worth they ſuffer dearth)</l>
               <l>There they his wealth, (which worldlings ſo deſire)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13835:60"/>There (that which only gentle mindes admire,</l>
               <l>And doth embelliſh wealth and parentage)</l>
               <l>His Learning and Religion entire:</l>
               <l>I, for my part, (how e're in this nice age</l>
               <l>It ſound but ill, and homely ſeeme) will ſpan</l>
               <l>His ſpatious praiſes thus, <hi>Hee was an honeſt man.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>(3)</head>
               <l>So leauing him to his eternall reſt,</l>
               <l>Let not my diſeſteemed Muſe offend,</l>
               <l>If my reſpect (which euer I profeſt</l>
               <l>Both to your ſelfe, and my much honord friend)</l>
               <l>Sad Lady, I to you now recommend.</l>
               <l>Whoſe griefe for his deceaſe (if you giue eare</l>
               <l>To your deare loue) will neuer haue an end:</l>
               <l>Nay but adde faith againſt deſpaire and feare,</l>
               <l>And pretious hope let in your boſome dwell,</l>
               <l>Wherein elſe differ Chriſtians fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Infidell?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>(4)</head>
               <l>He is not dead, whom you as dead lament,</l>
               <l>Only in the iourney which all once muſt goe,</l>
               <l>He you in time a little ouer-went:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13835:60"/>And euen in dutie (which all wiues doe owe,</l>
               <l>And wherein you much buxomneſſe wont ſhow)</l>
               <l>You him precedence may not well denie,</l>
               <l>Sith to prouide againſt your after woe,</l>
               <l>For your beſt comfort and ſocietie,</l>
               <l>He hath you left (till you two meet againe)</l>
               <l>The gages of his loue, the models of you twaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>(5)</head>
               <l>To whom, vouchſafe me leaue among the reſt</l>
               <l>Which honour you and your faire Familie,</l>
               <l>To wiſh all good, and of all good the beſt:</l>
               <l>Whereto Almighty God which ſitteth hie,</l>
               <l>Let ſay <hi>Amen:</hi> let all the Saints replie,</l>
               <l>And all the bleſſed Angels, which intend</l>
               <l>The care of man, this bleſſed note reuie:</l>
               <l>Ioy you await, and comfort them attend,</l>
               <l>Like ready handmaids, and what euer thing</l>
               <l>May theirs or your delight, or new contentment bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>(6)</head>
               <l>And if my praiers of any force may be,</l>
               <l>Such as the Palme in midſt of freſh Spring-tide</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13835:61"/>In ſome cleere cryſtall ſtreame her ſelfe doth ſee,</l>
               <l>And her ſtrait twigs, and branches ſpreading wide,</l>
               <l>Which goodly ſprowt and burgen from her ſide,</l>
               <l>With ſiluer bloſſomes rich embelliſhed,</l>
               <l>So may you ſee your young Imps multiplide,</l>
               <l>And grow vp thicke like ſeeds in gardens ſhed,</l>
               <l>And laſt your owne liues threed be drawne ſo ſmall,</l>
               <l>That (not a minute ere your time) like fruitfull ripe you fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>(7)</head>
               <l>Here ſtay my Muſe, and crauing pardon, kiſſe</l>
               <l>The vertuous hand of this ſad Lady Gent.</l>
               <l>Who to her ſex ſo worthy credit is,</l>
               <l>That for ten thouſand women which miſwent,</l>
               <l>Her gratious life and ſweet comportement</l>
               <l>Shall make amends, and take away the blame</l>
               <l>Wherewith they all their ſex haue ſham'd &amp; ſhent:</l>
               <l>For which her endleſſe praiſe and her good name</l>
               <l>Like pretious Incenſe ſhall on hie aſcend</l>
               <l>To heauen, and earth indeering her with God to friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
